<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pre-Columbian forest gardens span 180 km² in Bolivia’s
Iténez preserve</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2225-5827</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Gauthier</surname>
            <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Nicolas Gauthier</string-name>
          <role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff-1">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Florida Museum of Natural History, University of
Florida</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor-1"/>
      </author-notes>
      <history/>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Iténez Forest Preserve in the Bolivian Amazon spans 4,000 km²
between two of South America’s most significant archaeological
landscapes—yet until now it remained unmapped, a blank spot between
lowland Bolivia and the Brazilian Amazon. Using satellite imagery from
the driest months on record and an AI-assisted detection system, I
identified 180 km² of anthropogenic soils and forest gardens across the
preserve. These features, connected by dense networks of earthworks that
remain to be fully mapped, reveal organized landscape modification on a
scale comparable to the region’s famous earthwork complexes. The
findings demonstrate how ancient peoples transformed rainforest into
productive cultural landscapes whose ecological signatures persist
today, with local communities continuing to harvest cacao and other
useful species from these anthropogenic forests. This work illustrates
how AI can support—but not replace—human expertise in archaeological
detection at regional scales.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>For decades, a 4,000 km² void has persisted in archaeological maps
  of the Amazon, separating the well-studied earthwork landscapes of
  Bolivia from the forests of the Brazilian Amazon. The Iténez Forest
  Preserve occupies this glaring gap along the Bolivia-Brazil border.
  Located along the Bolivia-Brazil border between the extensively
  studied earthwork landscapes of the Bolivian lowlands and the forests
  of the Brazilian Amazon, this 4,000 km² expanse of forest remained
  largely unmapped by archaeologists. While important studies have
  documented sites at the preserve’s northern and southern margins
  (<xref alt="Robinson et al. 2021" rid="ref-robinson2021" ref-type="bibr">Robinson
  et al. 2021</xref>;
  <xref alt="Prümers, Jaimes Betancourt, and Plaza Martinez 2023" rid="ref-prümers2023" ref-type="bibr">Prümers,
  Jaimes Betancourt, and Plaza Martinez 2023</xref>;
  <xref alt="Carson et al. 2016" rid="ref-carson2016pre" ref-type="bibr">Carson
  et al. 2016</xref>) , the rugged interior—the vast majority of this
  territory—has remained archaeologically unknown. Dense canopy cover,
  remoteness, and lack of prior survey work in the interior left it a
  blank spot on regional maps—a void in our understanding of
  southwestern Amazonian prehistory. Its position between known centers
  of pre-Columbian engineering
  (<xref alt="Peripato et al. 2023" rid="ref-peripato2023" ref-type="bibr">Peripato
  et al. 2023</xref>;
  <xref alt="De Souza et al. 2018" rid="ref-desouza2018" ref-type="bibr">De
  Souza et al. 2018</xref>), however, suggested it might hold similar
  evidence of ancient landscape modification.</p>
      <p>This study fills that gap through systematic remote sensing
  analysis, revealing extensive anthropogenic landscapes hidden beneath
  the forest canopy. The work focuses specifically on detecting
  Amazonian Dark Earth (ADE) and associated forest gardens—patches of
  modified forest composition that mark ancient settlements and
  agricultural areas
  (<xref alt="Schmidt et al. 2014" rid="ref-schmidt2014" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt
  et al. 2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Palace et al. 2017" rid="ref-palace2017" ref-type="bibr">Palace
  et al. 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Goldberg et al. 2024" rid="ref-goldberg2024" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg
  et al. 2024</xref>) . While earthworks are noted where visible,
  comprehensive mapping of these features beneath the canopy remains for
  future work. This approach prioritizes the detection of anthropogenic
  soils and forest composition changes that represent the primary
  evidence of human landscape transformation in continuously forested
  regions.</p>
      <fig>
        <caption>
          <p>Sentinel-2 false color image composite of Itenez Forest
    Preserve from summer 2023. Light red spots indicate drier ,
    lowcanopy vegetation associated with anthropogenic forest gardens
    (palms, cacao, bamboo, and other economically useful
    plants).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/clipboard-2087942158.jpeg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The detection of these features at regional scale required
  developing new methodological approaches that combine AI-assisted
  pattern recognition with expert archaeological interpretation—a
  partnership where computational tools support but do not replace human
  expertise in identifying and mapping cultural landscapes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="image-selection-and-processing">
        <title>Image Selection and Processing</title>
        <p>I selected Sentinel-2 imagery
    (<xref alt="European Union/ESA/Copernicus 2017" rid="ref-copernicus_s2_sr_harmonized" ref-type="bibr">European
    Union/ESA/Copernicus 2017</xref>) from the driest periods in the
    satellite record (late summer 2023 and 2024), when reduced
    vegetation moisture and seasonal leaf loss maximize visibility of
    underlying soil and vegetation patterns. Cloud-free mosaics were
    processed in Google Earth Engine, combined with a state of the art
    regional canopy height model
    (<xref alt="Wagner et al. 2025" rid="ref-wagner2025highresolutiontreeheight" ref-type="bibr">Wagner
    et al. 2025</xref>) to distinguish anthropogenic forest structures
    from natural variation.</p>
        <fig>
          <caption>
            <p>False color Sentinel 2 image chips (left, center) and
      canopy height estimate (right). Anthropogenic forest patches
      appears as rounded patches of dry, low-canopy vegetation along
      terraces. Faint traces of earthworks and ditches can be seen
      surrounding and connecting the forest patches.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The imagery was exported as multi-scale tiles (512, 768, and 1024
    pixels) with band combinations optimized to highlight spectral
    signatures of ADE and modified forest. These signatures reflect the
    distinct ecological characteristics of anthropogenic landscapes:
    more open canopy structure, seasonal deciduousness, high
    concentrations of useful plants (palms, bamboos, cacao), and altered
    soil chemistry from centuries of human occupation and management
    Robinson et al.
    (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-robinson2021" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>
        <fig>
          <caption>
            <p>Detail of transition between natural forest vegetation
      (left) and anthropogenic forest (right). Not the lighter
      vegetation, lower canopy, and preponderance of palms and
      lianas.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/clipboard-593555342.png"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="detection-workflow-human-ai-partnership">
        <title>Detection Workflow: Human-AI Partnership</title>
        <p>I developed an agentic object detection system using GPT-4.1, and
    Moondream2 vision-language models to identify anthropogenic features
    at scale. This system serves as a detection and verification tool,
    supporting human expertise rather than replacing it. The workflow
    operates as follows:</p>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>GPT models review imagery and generate initial hypotheses
        about feature locations based on spectral patterns and landscape
        context. They are prompted to view the landscape holistically,
        looking for patterns across multiple domains, rather than
        focusing on strict quantitative criteria.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The primary models iteratively refine predictions through
        successive passes using a smaller, specialized vision language
        models tuned for object detection and grounding. These system
        lack the domain knowledge of the image contents, so the GPT
        agent must generate creative, abstract text prompts to detect
        all features in the scene (e.g. “reddish-pink spots”, “purple
        swirls”.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The system produces point predictions marking potential
        anthropogenic sites</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>These points guide large-scale verification and exploration
        of spatial patterns</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>Examples:</bold>
        </p>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png"/>
        <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** The scene is dominated by a continuous, mottled forest matrix. There 
are several compact, bright reddish-pink/magenta patches, especially in the 
lower left, lower center, and upper center-left. These patches are not simply 
at the forest edge or in open areas, but embedded within the forest, and some 
have lobate or elliptical forms. 
- **C2:** These same areas correspond to bright yellow/orange splotches, 
supporting the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation typical of ADE 
patches. The yellow/orange is compact and not overly diffuse.
- **CHM:** The compact reddish-pink patches in C1 correspond to areas of lower 
canopy height (darker blue/purple zones), sometimes with a ring or edge effect,
consistent with ADE patch structure.

**Spatial context:** The anomalies are within a continuous forest, not at the 
forest-nonforest boundary, and are not simply isolated forest islands. Some are
near the edge of a bluff or drainage, which fits expected ADE patch placement.

**Initial expert estimate:** There are at least 3–4 compact, plausible ADE-like
patches in this scene, possibly up to 5 if smaller lobate forms are included.

**Proceeding to Moondream object detection (Step 2).**

**First two prompts:**
- "reddish-pink spots"
- "magenta patches"</preformat>
        <preformat>**Synthesis of Moondream points (Step 3):**

- Both prompts ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned highly 
overlapping sets of points, indicating robust detection of the main anomalies.
- After removing duplicates, the following distinct compact patch locations are
identified:
  1. (0.0918, 0.2998) — Lower left, compact, strong dual spectral support, low 
CHM
  2. (0.292, 0.8223) — Lower center, compact, strong dual spectral support, low
CHM
  3. (0.4375, 0.7656) — Lower center-right, compact, strong dual spectral 
support, low CHM
  4. (0.6309, 0.5967) — Central, compact, strong dual spectral support, low CHM
  5. (0.7344, 0.1084) — Upper right, compact, strong dual spectral support, low
CHM
  6. (0.8486, 0.3789) — Right-central, compact, strong dual spectral support, 
low CHM

- The point at (0.9678, 0.6709) is near the extreme right edge and may be 
partially outside the main forest matrix, but still fits the context.
- All selected points are ≥5 ha, compact, and have supporting 
spectral/structural context.

**Summary of synthesis:**
- 6–7 distinct, compact ADE-like patches detected, all with strong dual 
spectral and CHM support.
- All are embedded in continuous forest, not at forest-nonforest boundaries.
- Points are robust across both detection prompts.
- No diffuse or edge-only anomalies included.
- All fit expected ADE patch form and context.

DONE.</preformat>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png"/>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png"/>
        <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** Several compact, bright reddish-pink/magenta patches are visible, 
especially to the right of the main drainage and near the center-right. These 
are distinct from the surrounding mottled forest matrix and are not simply 
forest-nonforest boundaries. Their form is compact and lobate, not diffuse.
- **C2:** These same areas correspond to bright yellow/orange splotches, 
supporting the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation typical of ADE 
patches.
- **CHM:** These patches do not correspond to clearings or sharp canopy gaps, 
but some show subtle lower-canopy signals, consistent with ADE forest 
structure.
- **Context:** The anomalies are within continuous forest, not at the edge or 
in floodplain, and are not recent disturbances. Their spatial patterning 
(clustered, not random) and proximity to drainage align with expected ADE 
context.

**Initial expert estimate:** 3–5 valid ADE-like patches (mainly in the right 
half of the image).

Proceeding to Moondream object detection for precise locations.</preformat>
        <preformat>**Synthesis (Step 3):**

- Both tool calls ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned nearly 
identical sets of points, confirming the robustness of the detections.
- After removing redundant points (duplicates within a few pixels), there are 5
distinct, compact patches that are well supported by both spectral images and 
context:
  1. (0.739, 0.663) — right-central, strong magenta/yellow
  2. (0.678, 0.347) — upper-right, compact, strong signal
  3. (0.891, 0.302) — far right, compact, strong signal
  4. (0.359, 0.546) — left-central, compact, moderate signal
  5. (0.090, 0.503) — far left, compact, moderate signal

- The remaining points (e.g., at the very bottom or edge) are either redundant 
or less well supported by context and spectral pattern.
- All selected patches are ≥5 ha, compact, and within continuous forest matrix,
not at forest edge or in floodplain.

**Summary:** 5 valid ADE-like patches detected, all with strong dual spectral 
support and appropriate context.

DONE.</preformat>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png"/>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png"/>
        <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** Several compact, lobate, reddish-pink/magenta patches are visible, 
especially in the lower and central portions of the image. These patches are 
embedded within a continuous forest matrix, not at the forest-nonforest 
boundary. Their form is compact and clustered, not diffuse.
- **C2:** The same locations show bright yellow/orange splotches, supporting 
the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation consistent with ADE patches.
- **CHM:** These areas correspond to subtle, compact zones of lower canopy 
height, sometimes with a ringed or clustered structure, further supporting the 
ADE hypothesis.

**Spatial context:** The anomalies are aligned along subtle drainage lines and 
are not simply forest islands or recent clearings. Their size and form are 
consistent with ADE patches (≥5 ha, compact, not diffuse).

**Initial expert estimate:** There are approximately 7–9 plausible ADE patches 
in this scene, based on the spectral and structural evidence.

Proceeding to Moondream object detection for precise point locations.</preformat>
        <preformat>**Synthesis (Step 3):**

- Both prompts ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned highly 
similar sets of points, confirming the robustness of the detection.
- After removing redundant/overlapping points and excluding those at the 
extreme image edge or lacking compact form/context, the following distinct, 
compact patches are validated:
  1. (0.410, 0.617) – central, strong spectral/structural support
  2. (0.412, 0.829) – lower central, strong support
  3. (0.500, 0.925) – lower center, strong support
  4. (0.605, 0.965) – lower right, strong support
  5. (0.778, 0.710) – right-central, strong support
  6. (0.834, 0.834) – lower right, strong support
  7. (0.832, 0.601) – mid-right, strong support
  8. (0.856, 0.335) – upper right, strong support
  9. (0.676, 0.336) – upper central, strong support
  10. (0.412, 0.267) – upper central, strong support

- Points at (0.156, 0.190), (0.028, 0.136), (0.163, 0.190), (0.032, 0.141), and
(0.781, 0.342), (0.681, 0.333) are either redundant or at the extreme edge with
less clear context, so are excluded.

**Final synthesis:** 10 distinct, compact ADE patch candidates, all with strong
dual spectral and structural support, compact form, and plausible context.

DONE.</preformat>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-10-1.png"/>
        <p>Critically, this AI component operated in parallel with detailed
    manual mapping. I meticulously reviewed and labeled hundreds of
    polygon boundaries over anthropogenic forest patches through careful
    imagery analysis, with the AI and manual mapping developing
    iteratively and informing each other. Earthworks—canals, ditches,
    and geometric earthworks—were recorded where visible through the
    canopy, though comprehensive mapping of these linear features
    remains a priority for future work with higher-resolution imagery.
    This approach allowed me to iteratively calibrate and validate the
    models’ ability to detect known archaeological features in zero-shot
    and few-shot learning contexts. The models were not fine-tuned but
    leveraged pre-trained capabilities to recognize visual patterns
    consistent with archaeological features. This approach exemplifies
    how AI can extend human capacity for regional-scale analysis without
    replacing the expertise necessary for accurate feature
    identification and interpretation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The analysis <bold>identified approximately 180 km² of
  anthropogenic soils and forest gardens within the Iténez Forest
  Preserve, representing 5% of its total area—comparable to the
  footprint of many modern world cities</bold>, though distributed as a
  network of patches rather than a contiguous area. I mapped over 350
  individual fields ranging from 5 to 700 hectares, with clear spatial
  clustering along bluffs, drainages, and floodplain margins in upland
  <italic>terra firme</italic> forest—confirming hypotheses about
  bluff-edge settlement systems previously proposed for this region
  (<xref alt="Denevan 1996" rid="ref-denevan1996" ref-type="bibr">Denevan
  1996</xref>).</p>
      <fig>
        <caption>
          <p>Anthropogenic forest patches.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png"/>
      </fig>
      <preformat>
|---------|---------|---------|---------|
=========================================
                                          </preformat>
      <fig>
        <caption>
          <p>Anthropogenic forest patches.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-11-2.png"/>
      </fig>
      <fig>
        <caption>
          <p>Manually labeled site locations (black) compared to
    automatically detected locations (red).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-12-1.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The most striking discovery is a major complex spanning more than 4
  kilometers, where large-scale fields connect through networks of
  earthworks. Across the mapped area, an exceptionally dense system of
  linear features links settlements into an integrated landscape. While
  full mapping of these earthworks awaits future work with
  canopy-penetrating sensors, their visible portions already demonstrate
  a level of landscape integration comparable to the most complex sites
  in neighboring regions.</p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/clipboard-4170918036.jpeg"/>
      <p>Rank-size analysis reveals a clear hierarchical structure in field
  sizes and site distribution, with the size distribution following a
  power law with an exponent close to 1 on log-log plots. This pattern,
  consistent with organized settlement systems, matches the scale and
  complexity documented in the Llanos de Mojos and Baures
  (<xref alt="Prümers et al. 2022" rid="ref-prumers2022lidar" ref-type="bibr">Prümers
  et al. 2022</xref>;
  <xref alt="Erickson 2000" rid="ref-erickson2000" ref-type="bibr">Erickson
  2000</xref>). The largest sites anchor networks of settlement and
  agroforestry patches, suggesting centralized planning and resource
  management across the landscape.</p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-13-1.png"/>
      <p>These anthropogenic landscapes remain ecologically distinct today.
  Forest composition in mapped areas shows high concentrations of
  economically useful species, particularly cacao, making the region a
  modern hotspot for wild cacao cultivation—a direct legacy of ancient
  land use practices
  (<xref alt="Carson et al. 2016" rid="ref-carson2016pre" ref-type="bibr">Carson
  et al. 2016</xref>) . Local and Indigenous communities continue to
  harvest these resources, underscoring that these are not merely
  archaeological sites but living landscapes where ancient management
  practices continue to shape both forest ecology and human
  livelihoods.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>These findings transform our understanding of the Iténez region
  from archaeological blank spot to critical piece in the Amazonian
  puzzle. The extent and organization of anthropogenic landscapes
  documented here match or exceed those in better-studied areas,
  confirming that large-scale landscape engineering extended
  continuously across the southwestern Amazon. This fills the last major
  gap in the regional archaeological map between the Llanos de Mojos and
  Baures, revealing that the Iténez was not a periphery but an integral
  part of pre-Columbian regional systems.</p>
      <p>The hierarchical site structure and extensive earthwork networks
  point to complex social organization capable of coordinating landscape
  modification across thousands of square kilometers. Rather than
  isolated communities practicing small-scale agriculture, the evidence
  suggests integrated regional systems linking settlements through
  engineered infrastructure and shared land management practices. The
  concentration of sites along bluff edges and floodplain margins
  confirms earlier hypotheses about settlement preferences in
  <italic>terra firme</italic> forests, while the scale revealed here
  exceeds previous expectations.</p>
      <p>The ecological legacy of these ancient landscapes extends beyond
  their archaeological significance. Forest composition in mapped areas
  reflects centuries of human selection for useful species, creating
  patches of anthropogenic forest that blur the line between nature and
  culture. The continued harvesting of cacao and other products from
  these forests by contemporary communities represents an unbroken
  tradition of forest management extending from pre-Columbian times to
  the present. This continuity challenges us to recognize that the
  “pristine” forests we seek to conserve are themselves products of
  Indigenous innovation and management.</p>
      <p>The successful detection of these features through combined AI and
  expert analysis demonstrates new possibilities for archaeological
  survey in forested regions. The human-AI partnership developed
  here—where computational tools assist in pattern detection while human
  expertise guides interpretation and mapping—offers a model for scaling
  archaeological survey across Amazonia’s vast forests. This approach
  proved particularly effective for identifying the subtle spectral
  signatures of anthropogenic soils and forest gardens that would be
  impossible to map at this scale through ground survey alone.</p>
      <sec id="implications-and-future-directions">
        <title>Implications and Future Directions</title>
        <p>This work contributes to the mounting evidence that the Amazon
    was extensively shaped by its pre-Columbian inhabitants, adding a
    major piece to our understanding of regional cultural landscapes.
    The Iténez landscapes join the growing inventory documented by
    recent synthetic works, while demonstrating that significant
    discoveries remain to be made even in the 21st century. The findings
    reinforce emerging models of pre-Columbian Amazonia as a mosaic of
    engineered landscapes rather than pristine wilderness punctuated by
    occasional cultural sites.</p>
        <p>Future research should pursue several directions. First, LiDAR or
    high-resolution radar imagery could reveal the full extent of
    earthwork networks currently hidden beneath the canopy, allowing
    comprehensive mapping of the linear features only partially visible
    in optical imagery. Second, systematic field verification and dating
    would establish the chronology and cultural affiliations of these
    landscapes, potentially revealing connections to known
    archaeological cultures of the Llanos de Mojos and Baures. Third,
    detailed ecological studies of forest composition and soil
    properties would deepen our understanding of how ancient management
    practices created the anthropogenic forests that communities value
    today. The methodological approach developed here—combining
    AI-assisted detection with expert archaeological
    interpretation—offers broader applications for Amazonian
    archaeology. As we refine these tools, maintaining the balance
    between computational efficiency and human expertise will be
    critical. AI can help us see patterns across vast scales, but
    understanding what those patterns mean for human history requires
    archaeological knowledge that no algorithm can replace.</p>
        <p>These findings also have immediate relevance for conservation
    planning. Protecting these forests means protecting both
    biodiversity and living Indigenous heritage—recognizing that the
    ecological richness we value today emerged from millennia of human
    management.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The Iténez Forest Preserve emerges from this analysis not as
  pristine wilderness but as a cultural landscape shaped by centuries of
  Indigenous management. The 180 km² of mapped anthropogenic soils and
  forest gardens, connected by dense earthwork networks and organized in
  hierarchical patterns, demonstrate that pre-Columbian peoples
  transformed this region as extensively as anywhere in Amazonia. This
  work fills the last major blank spot in the archaeological map of the
  southwestern Amazon, revealing continuous cultural landscapes between
  previously studied regions.</p>
      <p>These findings illustrate both the potential and limits of new
  technological approaches to archaeology. While AI-assisted detection
  enabled mapping at unprecedented scales, the interpretation and
  validation of these features required human expertise at every step.
  This partnership between computational tools and archaeological
  knowledge offers a path forward for understanding Amazonia’s human
  past across its vast forested expanses.</p>
      <p>As we continue to reveal the Amazon’s deep human history, we gain
  essential perspective on its present and future. The forest gardens
  where communities harvest cacao today are living monuments to
  Indigenous landscape management, reminding us that the biodiversity we
  value emerged from millennia of human-forest interaction.
  Understanding this legacy is crucial not only for archaeology but for
  contemporary efforts to conserve and sustainably manage these cultural
  landscapes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="appendix">
      <title>Appendix</title>
      <p>Comparison of tile-level site counts from observed data and
  zero-shot results from a variety of GPT models.</p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-14-1.png"/>
      <p>Performance metrics for zero-shot site detection:</p>
      <table-wrap>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">model</th>
              <th align="right">accuracy</th>
              <th align="right">sens</th>
              <th align="right">spec</th>
              <th align="right">f_meas</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">o4_mini</td>
              <td align="right">0.742</td>
              <td align="right">0.672</td>
              <td align="right">0.873</td>
              <td align="right">0.773</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">nano</td>
              <td align="right">0.681</td>
              <td align="right">0.950</td>
              <td align="right">0.175</td>
              <td align="right">0.796</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">agent</td>
              <td align="right">0.670</td>
              <td align="right">0.613</td>
              <td align="right">0.778</td>
              <td align="right">0.709</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">mini</td>
              <td align="right">0.654</td>
              <td align="right">0.664</td>
              <td align="right">0.635</td>
              <td align="right">0.715</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">gpt_4.1</td>
              <td align="right">0.637</td>
              <td align="right">0.513</td>
              <td align="right">0.873</td>
              <td align="right">0.649</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">o3</td>
              <td align="right">0.615</td>
              <td align="right">0.454</td>
              <td align="right">0.921</td>
              <td align="right">0.607</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Performance metrics for automated zero-shot site detection.</p>
      <p>Performance metrics for zero-shot site counting:</p>
      <table-wrap>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">model</th>
              <th align="right">rmse</th>
              <th align="right">mae</th>
              <th align="right">rsq</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">agent</td>
              <td align="right">2.910</td>
              <td align="right">1.852</td>
              <td align="right">0.460</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">o4_mini</td>
              <td align="right">3.063</td>
              <td align="right">1.901</td>
              <td align="right">0.486</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">mini</td>
              <td align="right">3.097</td>
              <td align="right">2.143</td>
              <td align="right">0.413</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">gpt_4.1</td>
              <td align="right">3.331</td>
              <td align="right">2.170</td>
              <td align="right">0.458</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">o3</td>
              <td align="right">3.637</td>
              <td align="right">2.379</td>
              <td align="right">0.404</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">nano</td>
              <td align="right">3.813</td>
              <td align="right">2.703</td>
              <td align="right">0.072</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Performance metrics for automated zero-shot site counting.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title/>
      <ref id="ref-carson2016pre">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>John F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayle</surname>
              <given-names>Francis E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitney</surname>
              <given-names>Bronwen S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriarte</surname>
              <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soto</surname>
              <given-names>J Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pre-columbian ring ditch construction and land use on a ‘chocolate forest island’in the bolivian amazon</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Quaternary Science</source>
          <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>347</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-copernicus_s2_sr_harmonized">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <string-name>European Union/ESA/Copernicus</string-name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Harmonized Sentinel-2 MSI: MultiSpectral Instrument, Level-2A (SR)</article-title>
          <publisher-name>Google Earth Engine</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <uri>https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/COPERNICUS_S2_SR_HARMONIZED</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-prumers2022lidar">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prümers</surname>
              <given-names>Heiko</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betancourt</surname>
              <given-names>Carla Jaimes</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriarte</surname>
              <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaich</surname>
              <given-names>Martin</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lidar reveals pre-hispanic low-density urbanism in the bolivian amazon</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK London</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <volume>606</volume>
          <issue>7913</issue>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>328</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-wagner2025highresolutiontreeheight">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>Fabien H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalagnol</surname>
              <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carter</surname>
              <given-names>Griffin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirye</surname>
              <given-names>Mayumi CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>Shivraj</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takougoum</surname>
              <given-names>Le Bienfaiteur Sagang</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Favrichon</surname>
              <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ometto</surname>
              <given-names>Jean PHB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>Lorena</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creze</surname>
              <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>George-Chacon</surname>
              <given-names>Stephanie P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Shuang</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Zhihua</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullissa</surname>
              <given-names>Adugna</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Yan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>Erone G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Worden</surname>
              <given-names>Sarah R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brandt</surname>
              <given-names>Martin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciais</surname>
              <given-names>Philippe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hagen</surname>
              <given-names>Stephen C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saatchi</surname>
              <given-names>Sassan</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>High resolution tree height mapping of the amazon forest using planet NICFI images and LiDAR-informed u-net model</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year>
          <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10600</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-denevan1996">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denevan</surname>
              <given-names>William M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A bluff model of riverine settlement in prehistoric amazonia</article-title>
          <source>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1467-8306.1996.tb01771.x</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8306.1996.tb01771.x</pub-id>
          <fpage>654</fpage>
          <lpage>681</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-robinson2021">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaimes-Betancourt</surname>
              <given-names>Carla</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elliott</surname>
              <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maezumi</surname>
              <given-names>S. Yoshi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hilbert</surname>
              <given-names>Lautaro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>Daiana</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Souza</surname>
              <given-names>Jonas Gregorio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriarte</surname>
              <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anthropogenic soil and settlement organisation in the Bolivian Amazon</article-title>
          <source>Geoarchaeology</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021-05">2021</year>
          <month>05</month>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/gea.21839</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gea.21839</pub-id>
          <fpage>388</fpage>
          <lpage>403</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-prümers2023">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prümers</surname>
              <given-names>Heiko</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaimes Betancourt</surname>
              <given-names>Carla</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plaza Martinez</surname>
              <given-names>Ruden</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Algunas tumbas prehispánicas de Bella Vista, Prov. Iténez, Bolivia</article-title>
          <source>Zeitschrift für Archäologie Außereuropäischer Kulturen</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2023-08-29">2023</year>
          <month>08</month>
          <day>29</day>
          <uri>https://publications.dainst.org/journals/zaak/article/view/4178</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.34780/AKD6-046J</pub-id>
          <fpage>251284 Seiten</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-schmidt2014">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapp Py-Daniel</surname>
              <given-names>Anne</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Paula Moraes</surname>
              <given-names>Claide</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valle</surname>
              <given-names>Raoni B. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caromano</surname>
              <given-names>Caroline F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Texeira</surname>
              <given-names>Wenceslau G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fonseca</surname>
              <given-names>João A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magalhães</surname>
              <given-names>Marcos P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva Do Carmo Santos</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Da Silva E Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Renan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guapindaia</surname>
              <given-names>Vera L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moraes</surname>
              <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lima</surname>
              <given-names>Helena P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neves</surname>
              <given-names>Eduardo G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
              <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dark earths and the human built landscape in Amazonia: a widespread pattern of anthrosol formation</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014-02">2014</year>
          <month>02</month>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <uri>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0305440313003889</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jas.2013.11.002</pub-id>
          <fpage>152</fpage>
          <lpage>165</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-palace2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Palace</surname>
              <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMichael</surname>
              <given-names>C. N. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braswell</surname>
              <given-names>B. H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hagen</surname>
              <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bush</surname>
              <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neves</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamanaha</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herrick</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frolking</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ancient Amazonian populations left lasting impacts on forest structure</article-title>
          <source>Ecosphere</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017-12">2017</year>
          <month>12</month>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <uri>https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ecs2.2035</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ecs2.2035</pub-id>
          <fpage>e02035</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-goldberg2024">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>Samuel L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Himmelstein</surname>
              <given-names>Joshua D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franchetto</surname>
              <given-names>Bruna</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lima</surname>
              <given-names>Helena</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watling</surname>
              <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moraes</surname>
              <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dorshow</surname>
              <given-names>Wetherbee B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fausto</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waura</surname>
              <given-names>Kumessi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
              <given-names>Huke</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
              <given-names>Taku Wate</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
              <given-names>Afukaka</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perron</surname>
              <given-names>J. Taylor</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Widespread Amazonian dark earth in the Xingu Indigenous Territory</article-title>
          <source>Nature Sustainability</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2024-07-26">2024</year>
          <month>07</month>
          <day>26</day>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-024-01399-3</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-024-01399-3</pub-id>
          <fpage>1304</fpage>
          <lpage>1312</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-peripato2023">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peripato</surname>
              <given-names>Vinicius</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levis</surname>
              <given-names>Carolina</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>Guido A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gamerman</surname>
              <given-names>Dani</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ter Steege</surname>
              <given-names>Hans</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitman</surname>
              <given-names>Nigel C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Souza</surname>
              <given-names>Jonas G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriarte</surname>
              <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Junqueira</surname>
              <given-names>André Braga</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trindade</surname>
              <given-names>Thiago B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>Fernando O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moraes</surname>
              <given-names>Claide De Paula</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lombardo</surname>
              <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamanaha</surname>
              <given-names>Eduardo K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maezumi</surname>
              <given-names>Shira Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ometto</surname>
              <given-names>Jean P. H. B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braga</surname>
              <given-names>José R. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campanharo</surname>
              <given-names>Wesley A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cassol</surname>
              <given-names>Henrique L. G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leal</surname>
              <given-names>Philipe R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Assis</surname>
              <given-names>Mauro L. R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Da Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Adriana M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>Oliver L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>Flávia R. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flores</surname>
              <given-names>Bernardo Monteiro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffman</surname>
              <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henkel</surname>
              <given-names>Terry W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umaña</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Natalia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magnusson</surname>
              <given-names>William E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valderrama Sandoval</surname>
              <given-names>Elvis H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barlow</surname>
              <given-names>Jos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Milliken</surname>
              <given-names>William</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopes</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Aparecida</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelo Fragomeni</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Andel</surname>
              <given-names>Tinde R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurance</surname>
              <given-names>Susan G. W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurance</surname>
              <given-names>William F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torres-Lezama</surname>
              <given-names>Armando</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Assis</surname>
              <given-names>Rafael L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molino</surname>
              <given-names>Jean-François</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mestre</surname>
              <given-names>Mickaël</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamblin</surname>
              <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coelho</surname>
              <given-names>Luiz De Souza</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lima Filho</surname>
              <given-names>Diogenes De Andrade</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittmann</surname>
              <given-names>Florian</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salomão</surname>
              <given-names>Rafael P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amaral</surname>
              <given-names>Iêda Leão</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guevara</surname>
              <given-names>Juan Ernesto</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Almeida Matos</surname>
              <given-names>Francisca Dionízia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castilho</surname>
              <given-names>Carolina V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carim</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelo De Jesus Veiga</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cárdenas López</surname>
              <given-names>Dairon</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sabatier</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Irume</surname>
              <given-names>Mariana Victória</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Pires</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guimarães</surname>
              <given-names>José Renan Da Silva</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bánki</surname>
              <given-names>Olaf S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piedade</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Teresa Fernandez</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>José Ferreira</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luize</surname>
              <given-names>Bruno Garcia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novo</surname>
              <given-names>Evlyn Márcia Moraes De Leão</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Núñez Vargas</surname>
              <given-names>Percy</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Thiago Sanna Freire</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venticinque</surname>
              <given-names>Eduardo Martins</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manzatto</surname>
              <given-names>Angelo Gilberto</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>Neidiane Farias Costa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terborgh</surname>
              <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casula</surname>
              <given-names>Katia Regina</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demarchi</surname>
              <given-names>Layon O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Honorio Coronado</surname>
              <given-names>Euridice N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monteagudo Mendoza</surname>
              <given-names>Abel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montero</surname>
              <given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schöngart</surname>
              <given-names>Jochen</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldpausch</surname>
              <given-names>Ted R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quaresma</surname>
              <given-names>Adriano Costa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aymard C.</surname>
              <given-names>Gerardo A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baraloto</surname>
              <given-names>Chris</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castaño Arboleda</surname>
              <given-names>Nicolás</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Engel</surname>
              <given-names>Julien</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petronelli</surname>
              <given-names>Pascal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zartman</surname>
              <given-names>Charles Eugene</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Killeen</surname>
              <given-names>Timothy J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marimon</surname>
              <given-names>Beatriz S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marimon-Junior</surname>
              <given-names>Ben Hur</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schietti</surname>
              <given-names>Juliana</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sousa</surname>
              <given-names>Thaiane R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasquez</surname>
              <given-names>Rodolfo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rincón</surname>
              <given-names>Lorena M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berenguer</surname>
              <given-names>Erika</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>Joice</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mostacedo</surname>
              <given-names>Bonifacio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Do Amaral</surname>
              <given-names>Dário Dantas</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castellanos</surname>
              <given-names>Hernán</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Medeiros</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelo Brilhante</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>Ana</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Camargo</surname>
              <given-names>José Luís</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farias</surname>
              <given-names>Emanuelle De Sousa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magalhães</surname>
              <given-names>José Leonardo Lima</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendonça Nascimento</surname>
              <given-names>Henrique Eduardo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Queiroz</surname>
              <given-names>Helder Lima</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brienen</surname>
              <given-names>Roel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardenas Revilla</surname>
              <given-names>Juan David</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stevenson</surname>
              <given-names>Pablo R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Araujo-Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>Alejandro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barçante Ladvocat Cintra</surname>
              <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feitosa</surname>
              <given-names>Yuri Oliveira</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa</surname>
              <given-names>Flávia Rodrigues</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carpanedo</surname>
              <given-names>Rainiellen De Sá</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duivenvoorden</surname>
              <given-names>Joost F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Noronha</surname>
              <given-names>Janaína Da Costa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
              <given-names>Domingos De Jesus</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mogollón</surname>
              <given-names>Hugo F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>Leandro Valle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Householder</surname>
              <given-names>John Ethan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lozada</surname>
              <given-names>José Rafael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Comiskey</surname>
              <given-names>James A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Draper</surname>
              <given-names>Freddie C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Toledo</surname>
              <given-names>José Julio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Damasco</surname>
              <given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dávila</surname>
              <given-names>Nállarett</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>García-Villacorta</surname>
              <given-names>Roosevelt</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopes</surname>
              <given-names>Aline</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornejo Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alonso</surname>
              <given-names>Alfonso</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dallmeier</surname>
              <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomes</surname>
              <given-names>Vitor H. F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jimenez</surname>
              <given-names>Eliana M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neill</surname>
              <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peñuela Mora</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Cristina</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Aguiar</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel P. P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arroyo</surname>
              <given-names>Luzmila</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antunes Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>Fernanda</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coelho De Souza</surname>
              <given-names>Fernanda</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feeley</surname>
              <given-names>Kenneth J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gribel</surname>
              <given-names>Rogerio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pansonato</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelo Petratti</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ríos Paredes</surname>
              <given-names>Marcos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brasil Da Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Izaias</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>Maria Julia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fine</surname>
              <given-names>Paul V. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fonty</surname>
              <given-names>Émile</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guedes</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelino Carneiro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Licona</surname>
              <given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pennington</surname>
              <given-names>Toby</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peres</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villa Zegarra</surname>
              <given-names>Boris Eduardo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parada</surname>
              <given-names>Germaine Alexander</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pardo Molina</surname>
              <given-names>Guido</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vos</surname>
              <given-names>Vincent Antoine</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cerón</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maas</surname>
              <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silveira</surname>
              <given-names>Marcos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stropp</surname>
              <given-names>Juliana</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>Raquel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>Tim R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daly</surname>
              <given-names>Doug</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huamantupa-Chuquimaco</surname>
              <given-names>Isau</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieira</surname>
              <given-names>Ima Célia Guimarães</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss Albuquerque</surname>
              <given-names>Bianca</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuentes</surname>
              <given-names>Alfredo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klitgaard</surname>
              <given-names>Bente</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcelo-Peña</surname>
              <given-names>José Luis</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silman</surname>
              <given-names>Miles R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tello</surname>
              <given-names>J. Sebastián</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vriesendorp</surname>
              <given-names>Corine</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chave</surname>
              <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Fiore</surname>
              <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hilário</surname>
              <given-names>Renato Richard</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>Juan Fernando</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivas-Torres</surname>
              <given-names>Gonzalo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Von Hildebrand</surname>
              <given-names>Patricio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>Luciana De Oliveira</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa</surname>
              <given-names>Edelcilio Marques</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Matos Bonates</surname>
              <given-names>Luiz Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doza</surname>
              <given-names>Hilda Paulette Dávila</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zárate Gómez</surname>
              <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallardo Gonzales</surname>
              <given-names>George Pepe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzales</surname>
              <given-names>Therany</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malhi</surname>
              <given-names>Yadvinder</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Andrade Miranda</surname>
              <given-names>Ires Paula</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mozombite Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>Linder Felipe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prieto</surname>
              <given-names>Adriana</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudas</surname>
              <given-names>Agustín</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruschel</surname>
              <given-names>Ademir R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Natalino</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vela</surname>
              <given-names>César I. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zent</surname>
              <given-names>Egleé L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zent</surname>
              <given-names>Stanford</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cano</surname>
              <given-names>Angela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carrero Márquez</surname>
              <given-names>Yrma Andreina</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Correa</surname>
              <given-names>Diego F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>Janaina Barbosa Pedrosa</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galbraith</surname>
              <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holmgren</surname>
              <given-names>Milena</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalamandeen</surname>
              <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lobo</surname>
              <given-names>Guilherme</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nascimento</surname>
              <given-names>Marcelo Trindade</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>Alexandre A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramirez-Angulo</surname>
              <given-names>Hirma</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rocha</surname>
              <given-names>Maira</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scudeller</surname>
              <given-names>Veridiana Vizoni</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sierra</surname>
              <given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tirado</surname>
              <given-names>Milton</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Der Heijden</surname>
              <given-names>Geertje</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vilanova Torre</surname>
              <given-names>Emilio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahuite Reategui</surname>
              <given-names>Manuel Augusto</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baider</surname>
              <given-names>Cláudia</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balslev</surname>
              <given-names>Henrik</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cárdenas</surname>
              <given-names>Sasha</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casas</surname>
              <given-names>Luisa Fernanda</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farfan-Rios</surname>
              <given-names>William</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>Cid</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Linares-Palomino</surname>
              <given-names>Reynaldo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendoza</surname>
              <given-names>Casimiro</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mesones</surname>
              <given-names>Italo</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urrego Giraldo</surname>
              <given-names>Ligia Estela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villarroel</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zagt</surname>
              <given-names>Roderick</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexiades</surname>
              <given-names>Miguel N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>Edmar Almeida</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Cabrera</surname>
              <given-names>Karina</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernandez</surname>
              <given-names>Lionel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palacios Cuenca</surname>
              <given-names>Walter</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pansini</surname>
              <given-names>Susamar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pauletto</surname>
              <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramirez Arevalo</surname>
              <given-names>Fredy</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sampaio</surname>
              <given-names>Adeilza Felipe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valenzuela Gamarra</surname>
              <given-names>Luis</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aragão</surname>
              <given-names>Luiz E. O. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>More than 10,000 pre-Columbian earthworks are still hidden throughout Amazonia</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2023-10-06">2023</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <day>06</day>
          <volume>382</volume>
          <issue>6666</issue>
          <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ade2541</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.ade2541</pub-id>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-desouza2018">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Souza</surname>
              <given-names>Jonas Gregorio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaan</surname>
              <given-names>Denise Pahl</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa</surname>
              <given-names>Antonia Damasceno</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aragão</surname>
              <given-names>Luiz E. O. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marimon</surname>
              <given-names>Ben Hur</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marimon</surname>
              <given-names>Beatriz Schwantes</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Da Silva</surname>
              <given-names>Izaias Brasil</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>Salman Saeed</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakahara</surname>
              <given-names>Francisco Ruji</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iriarte</surname>
              <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pre-Columbian earth-builders settled along the entire southern rim of the Amazon</article-title>
          <source>Nature Communications</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2018-03-27">2018</year>
          <month>03</month>
          <day>27</day>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-03510-7</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03510-7</pub-id>
          <fpage>1125</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-erickson2000">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Erickson</surname>
              <given-names>Clark L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An artificial landscape-scale fishery in the Bolivian Amazon</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
          <volume>408</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-heckenberger2008">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
              <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russell</surname>
              <given-names>J. Christian</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fausto</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toney</surname>
              <given-names>Joshua R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>Edithe</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franchetto</surname>
              <given-names>Bruna</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
              <given-names>Afukaka</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pre-Columbian Urbanism, Anthropogenic Landscapes, and the Future of the Amazon</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008-08-29">2008</year>
          <month>08</month>
          <day>29</day>
          <volume>321</volume>
          <issue>5893</issue>
          <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.1159769</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1159769</pub-id>
          <fpage>1214</fpage>
          <lpage>1217</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-6-nb-article">
    <front-stub>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pre-Columbian forest gardens span 180 km² in Bolivia’s
Iténez preserve</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2225-5827</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Gauthier</surname>
            <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Nicolas Gauthier</string-name>
          <role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1-nb-article">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff-1-nb-article">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Florida Museum of Natural History, University of
Florida</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor-1-nb-article"/>
      </author-notes>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Iténez Forest Preserve in the Bolivian Amazon spans 4,000 km²
between two of South America’s most significant archaeological
landscapes—yet until now it remained unmapped, a blank spot between
lowland Bolivia and the Brazilian Amazon. Using satellite imagery from
the driest months on record and an AI-assisted detection system, I
identified 180 km² of anthropogenic soils and forest gardens across the
preserve. These features, connected by dense networks of earthworks that
remain to be fully mapped, reveal organized landscape modification on a
scale comparable to the region’s famous earthwork complexes. The
findings demonstrate how ancient peoples transformed rainforest into
productive cultural landscapes whose ecological signatures persist
today, with local communities continuing to harvest cacao and other
useful species from these anthropogenic forests. This work illustrates
how AI can support—but not replace—human expertise in archaeological
detection at regional scales.</p>
      </abstract>
    </front-stub>
    <body>
      <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
        <code language="r script">library(here)</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>here() starts at /Users/nick/UFL Dropbox/Nicolas Gauthier/Projects/openai-to-z</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">library(tidyverse)</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>── Attaching core tidyverse packages ──────────────────────── tidyverse 2.0.0 ──
✔ dplyr     1.1.4     ✔ readr     2.1.5
✔ forcats   1.0.0     ✔ stringr   1.5.1
✔ ggplot2   3.5.2     ✔ tibble    3.3.0
✔ lubridate 1.9.4     ✔ tidyr     1.3.1
✔ purrr     1.0.4     </preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>── Conflicts ────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()
ℹ Use the conflicted package (&lt;http://conflicted.r-lib.org/&gt;) to force all conflicts to become errors</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">library(yardstick)</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>
Attaching package: 'yardstick'

The following object is masked from 'package:readr':

    spec</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">library(sf)</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>Linking to GEOS 3.13.1, GDAL 3.11.0, PROJ 9.6.0; sf_use_s2() is TRUE</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">library(mapview)
library(maptiles)
library(tidyterra)</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>
Attaching package: 'tidyterra'

The following object is masked from 'package:stats':

    filter</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">source(here('R/moondream.R'))</code>
        <boxed-text>
          <preformat>
Attaching package: 'jsonlite'

The following object is masked from 'package:purrr':

    flatten

Linking to: OpenSSL 3.3.2 3 Sep 2024</preformat>
        </boxed-text>
        <code language="r script">library(patchwork)
plot_nth_set_gg &lt;- function(lst, n, nrow = 1, ncol = 3) {
  # Get the nth list item
  if (length(lst) &lt; n) {
    stop("List doesn't have ", n, " items")
  }
  
  images &lt;- lst[[n]]
  
  plots &lt;- map(images, ~ {
    img &lt;- magick::image_read(.x)
    ggplot() +
      annotation_raster(as.raster(img), -Inf, Inf, -Inf, Inf) +
      theme_void() +
      coord_equal()
  })
  
  wrap_plots(plots, nrow = nrow, ncol = ncol)
}
get_sorted_files &lt;- function(pattern, dir = here('data/derived/tile_768')) {
  list.files(dir, recursive = TRUE, pattern = pattern, full.names = TRUE) |&gt;
    gtools::mixedsort()
}

create_image_triplets &lt;- function() {
  img_paths &lt;- c('geology', 'moisture', 'canopy') |&gt;
    paste0('_chip.jpg') |&gt;
    map(get_sorted_files)

  # Create list of triplets
  n_images &lt;- length(img_paths[[1]])
  map(1:n_images, ~list(
    c1 = img_paths[[1]][.x],
    c2 = img_paths[[2]][.x],
    chm = img_paths[[3]][.x]
  ))
}

triplets &lt;- create_image_triplets()
tiles &lt;- readRDS(here('data/derived/tiles_768_sf.rds'))</code>
      </sec>
      <sec id="introduction-nb-article">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <p>For decades, a 4,000 km² void has persisted in archaeological maps
  of the Amazon, separating the well-studied earthwork landscapes of
  Bolivia from the forests of the Brazilian Amazon. The Iténez Forest
  Preserve occupies this glaring gap along the Bolivia-Brazil border.
  Located along the Bolivia-Brazil border between the extensively
  studied earthwork landscapes of the Bolivian lowlands and the forests
  of the Brazilian Amazon, this 4,000 km² expanse of forest remained
  largely unmapped by archaeologists. While important studies have
  documented sites at the preserve’s northern and southern margins
  (<xref alt="Robinson et al. 2021" rid="ref-robinson2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Robinson
  et al. 2021</xref>;
  <xref alt="Prümers, Jaimes Betancourt, and Plaza Martinez 2023" rid="ref-prümers2023-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Prümers,
  Jaimes Betancourt, and Plaza Martinez 2023</xref>;
  <xref alt="Carson et al. 2016" rid="ref-carson2016pre-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Carson
  et al. 2016</xref>) , the rugged interior—the vast majority of this
  territory—has remained archaeologically unknown. Dense canopy cover,
  remoteness, and lack of prior survey work in the interior left it a
  blank spot on regional maps—a void in our understanding of
  southwestern Amazonian prehistory. Its position between known centers
  of pre-Columbian engineering
  (<xref alt="Peripato et al. 2023" rid="ref-peripato2023-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Peripato
  et al. 2023</xref>;
  <xref alt="De Souza et al. 2018" rid="ref-desouza2018-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">De
  Souza et al. 2018</xref>), however, suggested it might hold similar
  evidence of ancient landscape modification.</p>
        <p>This study fills that gap through systematic remote sensing
  analysis, revealing extensive anthropogenic landscapes hidden beneath
  the forest canopy. The work focuses specifically on detecting
  Amazonian Dark Earth (ADE) and associated forest gardens—patches of
  modified forest composition that mark ancient settlements and
  agricultural areas
  (<xref alt="Schmidt et al. 2014" rid="ref-schmidt2014-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt
  et al. 2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Palace et al. 2017" rid="ref-palace2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Palace
  et al. 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Goldberg et al. 2024" rid="ref-goldberg2024-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg
  et al. 2024</xref>) . While earthworks are noted where visible,
  comprehensive mapping of these features beneath the canopy remains for
  future work. This approach prioritizes the detection of anthropogenic
  soils and forest composition changes that represent the primary
  evidence of human landscape transformation in continuously forested
  regions.</p>
        <fig>
          <caption>
            <p>Sentinel-2 false color image composite of Itenez Forest
    Preserve from summer 2023. Light red spots indicate drier ,
    lowcanopy vegetation associated with anthropogenic forest gardens
    (palms, cacao, bamboo, and other economically useful
    plants).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/clipboard-2087942158.jpeg"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The detection of these features at regional scale required
  developing new methodological approaches that combine AI-assisted
  pattern recognition with expert archaeological interpretation—a
  partnership where computational tools support but do not replace human
  expertise in identifying and mapping cultural landscapes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="methods-nb-article">
        <title>Methods</title>
        <sec id="image-selection-and-processing-nb-article">
          <title>Image Selection and Processing</title>
          <p>I selected Sentinel-2 imagery
    (<xref alt="European Union/ESA/Copernicus 2017" rid="ref-copernicus_s2_sr_harmonized-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">European
    Union/ESA/Copernicus 2017</xref>) from the driest periods in the
    satellite record (late summer 2023 and 2024), when reduced
    vegetation moisture and seasonal leaf loss maximize visibility of
    underlying soil and vegetation patterns. Cloud-free mosaics were
    processed in Google Earth Engine, combined with a state of the art
    regional canopy height model
    (<xref alt="Wagner et al. 2025" rid="ref-wagner2025highresolutiontreeheight-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wagner
    et al. 2025</xref>) to distinguish anthropogenic forest structures
    from natural variation.</p>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_nth_set_gg(triplets, 58)</code>
            <fig>
              <caption>
                <p>False color Sentinel 2 image chips (left, center) and
      canopy height estimate (right). Anthropogenic forest patches
      appears as rounded patches of dry, low-canopy vegetation along
      terraces. Faint traces of earthworks and ditches can be seen
      surrounding and connecting the forest patches.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png"/>
            </fig>
          </sec>
          <p>The imagery was exported as multi-scale tiles (512, 768, and 1024
    pixels) with band combinations optimized to highlight spectral
    signatures of ADE and modified forest. These signatures reflect the
    distinct ecological characteristics of anthropogenic landscapes:
    more open canopy structure, seasonal deciduousness, high
    concentrations of useful plants (palms, bamboos, cacao), and altered
    soil chemistry from centuries of human occupation and management
    Robinson et al.
    (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-robinson2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>
          <fig>
            <caption>
              <p>Detail of transition between natural forest vegetation
      (left) and anthropogenic forest (right). Not the lighter
      vegetation, lower canopy, and preponderance of palms and
      lianas.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/clipboard-593555342.png"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="detection-workflow-human-ai-partnership-nb-article">
          <title>Detection Workflow: Human-AI Partnership</title>
          <p>I developed an agentic object detection system using GPT-4.1, and
    Moondream2 vision-language models to identify anthropogenic features
    at scale. This system serves as a detection and verification tool,
    supporting human expertise rather than replacing it. The workflow
    operates as follows:</p>
          <list list-type="order">
            <list-item>
              <p>GPT models review imagery and generate initial hypotheses
        about feature locations based on spectral patterns and landscape
        context. They are prompted to view the landscape holistically,
        looking for patterns across multiple domains, rather than
        focusing on strict quantitative criteria.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The primary models iteratively refine predictions through
        successive passes using a smaller, specialized vision language
        models tuned for object detection and grounding. These system
        lack the domain knowledge of the image contents, so the GPT
        agent must generate creative, abstract text prompts to detect
        all features in the scene (e.g. “reddish-pink spots”, “purple
        swirls”.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The system produces point predictions marking potential
        anthropogenic sites</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>These points guide large-scale verification and exploration
        of spatial patterns</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Examples:</bold>
          </p>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_nth_set_gg(triplets, 59)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">agent_test1 &lt;- detect_anthrosols(triplets[[59]], mode = 'gpt-4.1', echo = TRUE)</code>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** The scene is dominated by a continuous, mottled forest matrix. There 
are several compact, bright reddish-pink/magenta patches, especially in the 
lower left, lower center, and upper center-left. These patches are not simply 
at the forest edge or in open areas, but embedded within the forest, and some 
have lobate or elliptical forms. 
- **C2:** These same areas correspond to bright yellow/orange splotches, 
supporting the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation typical of ADE 
patches. The yellow/orange is compact and not overly diffuse.
- **CHM:** The compact reddish-pink patches in C1 correspond to areas of lower 
canopy height (darker blue/purple zones), sometimes with a ring or edge effect,
consistent with ADE patch structure.

**Spatial context:** The anomalies are within a continuous forest, not at the 
forest-nonforest boundary, and are not simply isolated forest islands. Some are
near the edge of a bluff or drainage, which fits expected ADE patch placement.

**Initial expert estimate:** There are at least 3–4 compact, plausible ADE-like
patches in this scene, possibly up to 5 if smaller lobate forms are included.

**Proceeding to Moondream object detection (Step 2).**

**First two prompts:**
- "reddish-pink spots"
- "magenta patches"</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_001(prompt = "reddish-pink spots")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.0918,"y":0.2998},{"x":0.292,"y":0.8223},{"x":0.4375,"y":0.7656},{…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_001(prompt = "magenta patches")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.4404,"y":0.7637},{"x":0.2949,"y":0.8213},{"x":0.0918,"y":0.2998},…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Synthesis of Moondream points (Step 3):**

- Both prompts ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned highly 
overlapping sets of points, indicating robust detection of the main anomalies.
- After removing duplicates, the following distinct compact patch locations are
identified:
  1. (0.0918, 0.2998) — Lower left, compact, strong dual spectral support, low 
CHM
  2. (0.292, 0.8223) — Lower center, compact, strong dual spectral support, low
CHM
  3. (0.4375, 0.7656) — Lower center-right, compact, strong dual spectral 
support, low CHM
  4. (0.6309, 0.5967) — Central, compact, strong dual spectral support, low CHM
  5. (0.7344, 0.1084) — Upper right, compact, strong dual spectral support, low
CHM
  6. (0.8486, 0.3789) — Right-central, compact, strong dual spectral support, 
low CHM

- The point at (0.9678, 0.6709) is near the extreme right edge and may be 
partially outside the main forest matrix, but still fits the context.
- All selected points are ≥5 ha, compact, and have supporting 
spectral/structural context.

**Summary of synthesis:**
- 6–7 distinct, compact ADE-like patches detected, all with strong dual 
spectral and CHM support.
- All are embedded in continuous forest, not at forest-nonforest boundaries.
- Points are robust across both detection prompts.
- No diffuse or edge-only anomalies included.
- All fit expected ADE patch form and context.

DONE.</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_detections(agent_test1)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_nth_set_gg(triplets, 59)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">agent_test2 &lt;- detect_anthrosols(triplets[[58]], mode = 'gpt-4.1', echo = TRUE)</code>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** Several compact, bright reddish-pink/magenta patches are visible, 
especially to the right of the main drainage and near the center-right. These 
are distinct from the surrounding mottled forest matrix and are not simply 
forest-nonforest boundaries. Their form is compact and lobate, not diffuse.
- **C2:** These same areas correspond to bright yellow/orange splotches, 
supporting the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation typical of ADE 
patches.
- **CHM:** These patches do not correspond to clearings or sharp canopy gaps, 
but some show subtle lower-canopy signals, consistent with ADE forest 
structure.
- **Context:** The anomalies are within continuous forest, not at the edge or 
in floodplain, and are not recent disturbances. Their spatial patterning 
(clustered, not random) and proximity to drainage align with expected ADE 
context.

**Initial expert estimate:** 3–5 valid ADE-like patches (mainly in the right 
half of the image).

Proceeding to Moondream object detection for precise locations.</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_002(prompt = "reddish-pink spots")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.7393,"y":0.6631},{"x":0.6777,"y":0.3467},{"x":0.8906,"y":0.3037},…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_002(prompt = "magenta patches")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.7412,"y":0.6641},{"x":0.6777,"y":0.3467},{"x":0.8916,"y":0.2998},…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Synthesis (Step 3):**

- Both tool calls ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned nearly 
identical sets of points, confirming the robustness of the detections.
- After removing redundant points (duplicates within a few pixels), there are 5
distinct, compact patches that are well supported by both spectral images and 
context:
  1. (0.739, 0.663) — right-central, strong magenta/yellow
  2. (0.678, 0.347) — upper-right, compact, strong signal
  3. (0.891, 0.302) — far right, compact, strong signal
  4. (0.359, 0.546) — left-central, compact, moderate signal
  5. (0.090, 0.503) — far left, compact, moderate signal

- The remaining points (e.g., at the very bottom or edge) are either redundant 
or less well supported by context and spectral pattern.
- All selected patches are ≥5 ha, compact, and within continuous forest matrix,
not at forest edge or in floodplain.

**Summary:** 5 valid ADE-like patches detected, all with strong dual spectral 
support and appropriate context.

DONE.</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_detections(agent_test2)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_nth_set_gg(triplets, 59)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">agent_test3 &lt;- detect_anthrosols(triplets[[50]], mode = 'gpt-4.1', echo = TRUE)</code>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Scene interpretation (Step 1):**

- **C1:** Several compact, lobate, reddish-pink/magenta patches are visible, 
especially in the lower and central portions of the image. These patches are 
embedded within a continuous forest matrix, not at the forest-nonforest 
boundary. Their form is compact and clustered, not diffuse.
- **C2:** The same locations show bright yellow/orange splotches, supporting 
the interpretation of stressed/drier vegetation consistent with ADE patches.
- **CHM:** These areas correspond to subtle, compact zones of lower canopy 
height, sometimes with a ringed or clustered structure, further supporting the 
ADE hypothesis.

**Spatial context:** The anomalies are aligned along subtle drainage lines and 
are not simply forest islands or recent clearings. Their size and form are 
consistent with ADE patches (≥5 ha, compact, not diffuse).

**Initial expert estimate:** There are approximately 7–9 plausible ADE patches 
in this scene, based on the spectral and structural evidence.

Proceeding to Moondream object detection for precise point locations.</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_003(prompt = "reddish-pink spots")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.4102,"y":0.6172},{"x":0.4121,"y":0.8291},{"x":0.5,"y":0.9248},{"x…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>◯ [tool call] tool_003(prompt = "magenta patches")</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>● #&gt; [{"x":0.4092,"y":0.6172},{"x":0.4092,"y":0.8291},{"x":0.5,"y":0.9248},{"x…</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
            <boxed-text>
              <preformat>**Synthesis (Step 3):**

- Both prompts ("reddish-pink spots", "magenta patches") returned highly 
similar sets of points, confirming the robustness of the detection.
- After removing redundant/overlapping points and excluding those at the 
extreme image edge or lacking compact form/context, the following distinct, 
compact patches are validated:
  1. (0.410, 0.617) – central, strong spectral/structural support
  2. (0.412, 0.829) – lower central, strong support
  3. (0.500, 0.925) – lower center, strong support
  4. (0.605, 0.965) – lower right, strong support
  5. (0.778, 0.710) – right-central, strong support
  6. (0.834, 0.834) – lower right, strong support
  7. (0.832, 0.601) – mid-right, strong support
  8. (0.856, 0.335) – upper right, strong support
  9. (0.676, 0.336) – upper central, strong support
  10. (0.412, 0.267) – upper central, strong support

- Points at (0.156, 0.190), (0.028, 0.136), (0.163, 0.190), (0.032, 0.141), and
(0.781, 0.342), (0.681, 0.333) are either redundant or at the extreme edge with
less clear context, so are excluded.

**Final synthesis:** 10 distinct, compact ADE patch candidates, all with strong
dual spectral and structural support, compact form, and plausible context.

DONE.</preformat>
            </boxed-text>
          </sec>
          <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
            <code language="r script">plot_detections(agent_test3)</code>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-10-1.png"/>
          </sec>
          <p>Critically, this AI component operated in parallel with detailed
    manual mapping. I meticulously reviewed and labeled hundreds of
    polygon boundaries over anthropogenic forest patches through careful
    imagery analysis, with the AI and manual mapping developing
    iteratively and informing each other. Earthworks—canals, ditches,
    and geometric earthworks—were recorded where visible through the
    canopy, though comprehensive mapping of these linear features
    remains a priority for future work with higher-resolution imagery.
    This approach allowed me to iteratively calibrate and validate the
    models’ ability to detect known archaeological features in zero-shot
    and few-shot learning contexts. The models were not fine-tuned but
    leveraged pre-trained capabilities to recognize visual patterns
    consistent with archaeological features. This approach exemplifies
    how AI can extend human capacity for regional-scale analysis without
    replacing the expertise necessary for accurate feature
    identification and interpretation.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="results-nb-article">
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>The analysis <bold>identified approximately 180 km² of
  anthropogenic soils and forest gardens within the Iténez Forest
  Preserve, representing 5% of its total area—comparable to the
  footprint of many modern world cities</bold>, though distributed as a
  network of patches rather than a contiguous area. I mapped over 350
  individual fields ranging from 5 to 700 hectares, with clear spatial
  clustering along bluffs, drainages, and floodplain margins in upland
  <italic>terra firme</italic> forest—confirming hypotheses about
  bluff-edge settlement systems previously proposed for this region
  (<xref alt="Denevan 1996" rid="ref-denevan1996-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Denevan
  1996</xref>).</p>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script">anthrosols &lt;- read_sf('data/derived/anthrosols.gpkg') |&gt;
    mutate(area = units::set_units(st_area(geom), km2) |&gt; units::drop_units())

mapview(anthrosols, basemaps = 'Esri.WorldImagery')</code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>file:////private/var/folders/pt/mdk8gblx1f30vm94rgg1582r0000gn/T/Rtmp4QjdrZ/filecbed4e898912/widgetcbed27862506.html screenshot completed</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <fig>
            <caption>
              <p>Anthropogenic forest patches.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png"/>
          </fig>
          <code language="r script"># Get tiles automatically based on your data extent
elev_tiles &lt;- get_tiles(st_bbox(anthrosols) |&gt; st_as_sfc() |&gt; st_buffer(10000), 
                        provider = "Esri.NatGeoWorldMap", zoom = 11, verbose = FALSE) </code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>
|---------|---------|---------|---------|
=========================================
                                          </preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <code language="r script">ggplot() +
  geom_spatraster_rgb(data = elev_tiles) +  # basemap
  geom_sf(data = st_centroid(anthrosols), aes(size = area)) +  
  scale_size_area(name = 'area (km2)') +
  coord_sf(crs = st_crs(elev_tiles)) +
  theme_void()</code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>&lt;SpatRaster&gt; resampled to 500778 cells.</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>Warning: st_centroid assumes attributes are constant over geometries</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <fig>
            <caption>
              <p>Anthropogenic forest patches.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-11-2.png"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script">convert_tile_points &lt;- function(points_tibble, tile_geom) {
  # Get bounding box of the tile
  bbox &lt;- st_bbox(tile_geom)
  # Convert normalized coordinates to spatial coordinates
  points_tibble %&gt;%
    mutate(
      spatial_x = bbox["xmin"] + x * (bbox["xmax"] - bbox["xmin"]),
      spatial_y = bbox["ymin"] + y * (bbox["ymax"] - bbox["ymin"])
    )
}

combine_all_points &lt;- function(points_list, tiles_list) {
  # Convert all and add tile index
  spatial_list &lt;- map2(points_list, tiles_list, convert_tile_points) %&gt;%
    imap(~ mutate(.x, tile_id = .y))  # Add tile identifier
  
  # Combine all tibbles
  all_points &lt;- bind_rows(spatial_list)
  
  # Convert to sf using CRS from first tile
  all_points %&gt;%
    st_as_sf(coords = c("spatial_x", "spatial_y"), 
             crs =4326)
}

agent_results &lt;- readRDS(here('data/derived/moon_41.rds'))

agent_points &lt;- map(agent_results, ~.x$result$points) |&gt;
  combine_all_points(tiles$geom) |&gt;
  select(-x, -y)

ggplot() +
  geom_spatraster_rgb(data = elev_tiles) +  # basemap
  geom_sf(data = st_centroid(anthrosols),fill = 'black') +
  geom_sf(data = agent_points, size = 1, color = 'red') +
  coord_sf(crs = st_crs(elev_tiles)) +
  theme_void()</code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>&lt;SpatRaster&gt; resampled to 500778 cells.</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>Warning: st_centroid assumes attributes are constant over geometries</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <fig>
            <caption>
              <p>Manually labeled site locations (black) compared to
    automatically detected locations (red).</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-12-1.png"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <p>The most striking discovery is a major complex spanning more than 4
  kilometers, where large-scale fields connect through networks of
  earthworks. Across the mapped area, an exceptionally dense system of
  linear features links settlements into an integrated landscape. While
  full mapping of these earthworks awaits future work with
  canopy-penetrating sensors, their visible portions already demonstrate
  a level of landscape integration comparable to the most complex sites
  in neighboring regions.</p>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/clipboard-4170918036.jpeg"/>
        <p>Rank-size analysis reveals a clear hierarchical structure in field
  sizes and site distribution, with the size distribution following a
  power law with an exponent close to 1 on log-log plots. This pattern,
  consistent with organized settlement systems, matches the scale and
  complexity documented in the Llanos de Mojos and Baures
  (<xref alt="Prümers et al. 2022" rid="ref-prumers2022lidar-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Prümers
  et al. 2022</xref>;
  <xref alt="Erickson 2000" rid="ref-erickson2000-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Erickson
  2000</xref>). The largest sites anchor networks of settlement and
  agroforestry patches, suggesting centralized planning and resource
  management across the landscape.</p>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script"># Prepare data for rank size plot
rank_size_data &lt;- anthrosols %&gt;%
  arrange(desc(area)) %&gt;%
  mutate(rank = row_number())

# Add trend line to check for Zipf's law
ggplot(rank_size_data, aes(x = rank, y = area)) +
  geom_point(size = 3, color = "red") +
  geom_smooth(method = "lm", se = TRUE, color = "black", linetype = "dashed") +
  scale_x_log10() +
  scale_y_log10() +
  labs(title = "Rank Size Plot with Trend Line",
       x = "Rank (log scale)",
       y = "Area (log scale)",
       subtitle = "Dashed line shows linear fit in log-log space") +
  theme_minimal()</code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>`geom_smooth()` using formula = 'y ~ x'</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-13-1.png"/>
        </sec>
        <p>These anthropogenic landscapes remain ecologically distinct today.
  Forest composition in mapped areas shows high concentrations of
  economically useful species, particularly cacao, making the region a
  modern hotspot for wild cacao cultivation—a direct legacy of ancient
  land use practices
  (<xref alt="Carson et al. 2016" rid="ref-carson2016pre-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Carson
  et al. 2016</xref>) . Local and Indigenous communities continue to
  harvest these resources, underscoring that these are not merely
  archaeological sites but living landscapes where ancient management
  practices continue to shape both forest ecology and human
  livelihoods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="discussion-nb-article">
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <p>These findings transform our understanding of the Iténez region
  from archaeological blank spot to critical piece in the Amazonian
  puzzle. The extent and organization of anthropogenic landscapes
  documented here match or exceed those in better-studied areas,
  confirming that large-scale landscape engineering extended
  continuously across the southwestern Amazon. This fills the last major
  gap in the regional archaeological map between the Llanos de Mojos and
  Baures, revealing that the Iténez was not a periphery but an integral
  part of pre-Columbian regional systems.</p>
        <p>The hierarchical site structure and extensive earthwork networks
  point to complex social organization capable of coordinating landscape
  modification across thousands of square kilometers. Rather than
  isolated communities practicing small-scale agriculture, the evidence
  suggests integrated regional systems linking settlements through
  engineered infrastructure and shared land management practices. The
  concentration of sites along bluff edges and floodplain margins
  confirms earlier hypotheses about settlement preferences in
  <italic>terra firme</italic> forests, while the scale revealed here
  exceeds previous expectations.</p>
        <p>The ecological legacy of these ancient landscapes extends beyond
  their archaeological significance. Forest composition in mapped areas
  reflects centuries of human selection for useful species, creating
  patches of anthropogenic forest that blur the line between nature and
  culture. The continued harvesting of cacao and other products from
  these forests by contemporary communities represents an unbroken
  tradition of forest management extending from pre-Columbian times to
  the present. This continuity challenges us to recognize that the
  “pristine” forests we seek to conserve are themselves products of
  Indigenous innovation and management.</p>
        <p>The successful detection of these features through combined AI and
  expert analysis demonstrates new possibilities for archaeological
  survey in forested regions. The human-AI partnership developed
  here—where computational tools assist in pattern detection while human
  expertise guides interpretation and mapping—offers a model for scaling
  archaeological survey across Amazonia’s vast forests. This approach
  proved particularly effective for identifying the subtle spectral
  signatures of anthropogenic soils and forest gardens that would be
  impossible to map at this scale through ground survey alone.</p>
        <sec id="implications-and-future-directions-nb-article">
          <title>Implications and Future Directions</title>
          <p>This work contributes to the mounting evidence that the Amazon
    was extensively shaped by its pre-Columbian inhabitants, adding a
    major piece to our understanding of regional cultural landscapes.
    The Iténez landscapes join the growing inventory documented by
    recent synthetic works, while demonstrating that significant
    discoveries remain to be made even in the 21st century. The findings
    reinforce emerging models of pre-Columbian Amazonia as a mosaic of
    engineered landscapes rather than pristine wilderness punctuated by
    occasional cultural sites.</p>
          <p>Future research should pursue several directions. First, LiDAR or
    high-resolution radar imagery could reveal the full extent of
    earthwork networks currently hidden beneath the canopy, allowing
    comprehensive mapping of the linear features only partially visible
    in optical imagery. Second, systematic field verification and dating
    would establish the chronology and cultural affiliations of these
    landscapes, potentially revealing connections to known
    archaeological cultures of the Llanos de Mojos and Baures. Third,
    detailed ecological studies of forest composition and soil
    properties would deepen our understanding of how ancient management
    practices created the anthropogenic forests that communities value
    today. The methodological approach developed here—combining
    AI-assisted detection with expert archaeological
    interpretation—offers broader applications for Amazonian
    archaeology. As we refine these tools, maintaining the balance
    between computational efficiency and human expertise will be
    critical. AI can help us see patterns across vast scales, but
    understanding what those patterns mean for human history requires
    archaeological knowledge that no algorithm can replace.</p>
          <p>These findings also have immediate relevance for conservation
    planning. Protecting these forests means protecting both
    biodiversity and living Indigenous heritage—recognizing that the
    ecological richness we value today emerged from millennia of human
    management.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="conclusion-nb-article">
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p>The Iténez Forest Preserve emerges from this analysis not as
  pristine wilderness but as a cultural landscape shaped by centuries of
  Indigenous management. The 180 km² of mapped anthropogenic soils and
  forest gardens, connected by dense earthwork networks and organized in
  hierarchical patterns, demonstrate that pre-Columbian peoples
  transformed this region as extensively as anywhere in Amazonia. This
  work fills the last major blank spot in the archaeological map of the
  southwestern Amazon, revealing continuous cultural landscapes between
  previously studied regions.</p>
        <p>These findings illustrate both the potential and limits of new
  technological approaches to archaeology. While AI-assisted detection
  enabled mapping at unprecedented scales, the interpretation and
  validation of these features required human expertise at every step.
  This partnership between computational tools and archaeological
  knowledge offers a path forward for understanding Amazonia’s human
  past across its vast forested expanses.</p>
        <p>As we continue to reveal the Amazon’s deep human history, we gain
  essential perspective on its present and future. The forest gardens
  where communities harvest cacao today are living monuments to
  Indigenous landscape management, reminding us that the biodiversity we
  value emerged from millennia of human-forest interaction.
  Understanding this legacy is crucial not only for archaeology but for
  contemporary efforts to conserve and sustainably manage these cultural
  landscapes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="appendix-nb-article">
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <p>Comparison of tile-level site counts from observed data and
  zero-shot results from a variety of GPT models.</p>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script">results &lt;- readRDS(here('data/derived/results.rds')) |&gt;
  mutate(.truth = lengths(st_intersects(geometry, anthrosols)),
         centroids = lengths(st_intersects(geometry, st_centroid(anthrosols))),
         agent = map_dbl(agent_results, ~.x$result$count)
)</code>
          <boxed-text>
            <preformat>Warning: There was 1 warning in `stopifnot()`.
ℹ In argument: `centroids = lengths(st_intersects(geometry,
  st_centroid(anthrosols)))`.
Caused by warning:
! st_centroid assumes attributes are constant over geometries</preformat>
          </boxed-text>
          <code language="r script">results |&gt;
  select(-id, -.truth, -nano) |&gt;
  rename(.observed_sites = centroids) |&gt;
 pivot_longer(-geometry) |&gt;
ggplot() +
  geom_sf(aes(fill = value)) +
  facet_wrap(~name) +
  scale_fill_viridis_c(name = 'Site count') +
  theme_bw()</code>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-14-1.png"/>
        </sec>
        <p>Performance metrics for zero-shot site detection:</p>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script">site_detection_metrics &lt;- metric_set(accuracy, sens, spec, f_meas)

results |&gt;
  select(-.truth) |&gt;
  st_drop_geometry() |&gt;
  pivot_longer(-c(id, centroids), names_to = 'model', values_to = 'estimate') |&gt;
  group_by(model) |&gt;
  mutate(estimate = factor(estimate &gt; 0),
         truth = factor(centroids &gt; 0)) |&gt;
  site_detection_metrics(truth = truth, estimate = estimate, event_level = 'second') |&gt;
  select(-.estimator) |&gt;
  pivot_wider(names_from = .metric, values_from = .estimate) |&gt;
  mutate(across(where(is.numeric), ~ round(.x, 3))) %&gt;%
  arrange(desc(accuracy)) |&gt;
  kableExtra::kable()</code>
          <table-wrap>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">model</th>
                  <th align="right">accuracy</th>
                  <th align="right">sens</th>
                  <th align="right">spec</th>
                  <th align="right">f_meas</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">o4_mini</td>
                  <td align="right">0.742</td>
                  <td align="right">0.672</td>
                  <td align="right">0.873</td>
                  <td align="right">0.773</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">nano</td>
                  <td align="right">0.681</td>
                  <td align="right">0.950</td>
                  <td align="right">0.175</td>
                  <td align="right">0.796</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">agent</td>
                  <td align="right">0.670</td>
                  <td align="right">0.613</td>
                  <td align="right">0.778</td>
                  <td align="right">0.709</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">mini</td>
                  <td align="right">0.654</td>
                  <td align="right">0.664</td>
                  <td align="right">0.635</td>
                  <td align="right">0.715</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">gpt_4.1</td>
                  <td align="right">0.637</td>
                  <td align="right">0.513</td>
                  <td align="right">0.873</td>
                  <td align="right">0.649</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">o3</td>
                  <td align="right">0.615</td>
                  <td align="right">0.454</td>
                  <td align="right">0.921</td>
                  <td align="right">0.607</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>Performance metrics for automated zero-shot site detection.</p>
        </sec>
        <p>Performance metrics for zero-shot site counting:</p>
        <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
          <code language="r script">regression_metrics &lt;- metric_set(rmse, mae, rsq)

results |&gt;
  select(-.truth) |&gt;
  st_drop_geometry() |&gt;
  pivot_longer(-c(id, centroids), names_to = 'model', values_to = 'estimate') |&gt;
  group_by(model) |&gt;
  mutate(estimate = pmax(estimate, 1e-6)) |&gt;
  regression_metrics(truth = centroids, estimate = estimate) |&gt;
  select(-.estimator) |&gt;
  pivot_wider(names_from = .metric, values_from = .estimate) |&gt;
  mutate(across(where(is.numeric), ~ round(.x, 3))) %&gt;%
  arrange(rmse) |&gt;
  kableExtra::kable()</code>
          <table-wrap>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">model</th>
                  <th align="right">rmse</th>
                  <th align="right">mae</th>
                  <th align="right">rsq</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">agent</td>
                  <td align="right">2.910</td>
                  <td align="right">1.852</td>
                  <td align="right">0.460</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">o4_mini</td>
                  <td align="right">3.063</td>
                  <td align="right">1.901</td>
                  <td align="right">0.486</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">mini</td>
                  <td align="right">3.097</td>
                  <td align="right">2.143</td>
                  <td align="right">0.413</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">gpt_4.1</td>
                  <td align="right">3.331</td>
                  <td align="right">2.170</td>
                  <td align="right">0.458</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">o3</td>
                  <td align="right">3.637</td>
                  <td align="right">2.379</td>
                  <td align="right">0.404</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left">nano</td>
                  <td align="right">3.813</td>
                  <td align="right">2.703</td>
                  <td align="right">0.072</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>Performance metrics for automated zero-shot site counting.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <title/>
        <ref id="ref-carson2016pre-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Carson</surname>
                <given-names>John F</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mayle</surname>
                <given-names>Francis E</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Whitney</surname>
                <given-names>Bronwen S</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Iriarte</surname>
                <given-names>José</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Soto</surname>
                <given-names>J Daniel</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Pre-columbian ring ditch construction and land use on a ‘chocolate forest island’in the bolivian amazon</article-title>
            <source>Journal of Quaternary Science</source>
            <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
            <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
            <volume>31</volume>
            <issue>4</issue>
            <fpage>337</fpage>
            <lpage>347</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-copernicus_s2_sr_harmonized-nb-article">
          <element-citation>
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <string-name>European Union/ESA/Copernicus</string-name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Harmonized Sentinel-2 MSI: MultiSpectral Instrument, Level-2A (SR)</article-title>
            <publisher-name>Google Earth Engine</publisher-name>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
            <uri>https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/COPERNICUS_S2_SR_HARMONIZED</uri>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-prumers2022lidar-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Prümers</surname>
                <given-names>Heiko</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Betancourt</surname>
                <given-names>Carla Jaimes</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Iriarte</surname>
                <given-names>José</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Robinson</surname>
                <given-names>Mark</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schaich</surname>
                <given-names>Martin</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Lidar reveals pre-hispanic low-density urbanism in the bolivian amazon</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK London</publisher-name>
            <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
            <volume>606</volume>
            <issue>7913</issue>
            <fpage>325</fpage>
            <lpage>328</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-wagner2025highresolutiontreeheight-nb-article">
          <element-citation>
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Wagner</surname>
                <given-names>Fabien H</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Dalagnol</surname>
                <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Carter</surname>
                <given-names>Griffin</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hirye</surname>
                <given-names>Mayumi CM</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gill</surname>
                <given-names>Shivraj</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Takougoum</surname>
                <given-names>Le Bienfaiteur Sagang</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Favrichon</surname>
                <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Keller</surname>
                <given-names>Michael</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ometto</surname>
                <given-names>Jean PHB</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Alves</surname>
                <given-names>Lorena</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Creze</surname>
                <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>George-Chacon</surname>
                <given-names>Stephanie P</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Li</surname>
                <given-names>Shuang</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Liu</surname>
                <given-names>Zhihua</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mullissa</surname>
                <given-names>Adugna</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Yang</surname>
                <given-names>Yan</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Santos</surname>
                <given-names>Erone G</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Worden</surname>
                <given-names>Sarah R</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Brandt</surname>
                <given-names>Martin</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ciais</surname>
                <given-names>Philippe</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hagen</surname>
                <given-names>Stephen C</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Saatchi</surname>
                <given-names>Sassan</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>High resolution tree height mapping of the amazon forest using planet NICFI images and LiDAR-informed u-net model</article-title>
            <year iso-8601-date="2025">2025</year>
            <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10600</uri>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-denevan1996-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Denevan</surname>
                <given-names>William M.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>A bluff model of riverine settlement in prehistoric amazonia</article-title>
            <source>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
            <volume>86</volume>
            <issue>4</issue>
            <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1467-8306.1996.tb01771.x</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8306.1996.tb01771.x</pub-id>
            <fpage>654</fpage>
            <lpage>681</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-robinson2021-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Robinson</surname>
                <given-names>Mark</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Jaimes-Betancourt</surname>
                <given-names>Carla</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Elliott</surname>
                <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Maezumi</surname>
                <given-names>S. Yoshi</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hilbert</surname>
                <given-names>Lautaro</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Alves</surname>
                <given-names>Daiana</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Souza</surname>
                <given-names>Jonas Gregorio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Iriarte</surname>
                <given-names>José</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Anthropogenic soil and settlement organisation in the Bolivian Amazon</article-title>
            <source>Geoarchaeology</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2021-05">2021</year>
            <month>05</month>
            <volume>36</volume>
            <issue>3</issue>
            <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/gea.21839</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gea.21839</pub-id>
            <fpage>388</fpage>
            <lpage>403</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-prümers2023-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Prümers</surname>
                <given-names>Heiko</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Jaimes Betancourt</surname>
                <given-names>Carla</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Plaza Martinez</surname>
                <given-names>Ruden</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Algunas tumbas prehispánicas de Bella Vista, Prov. Iténez, Bolivia</article-title>
            <source>Zeitschrift für Archäologie Außereuropäischer Kulturen</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-08-29">2023</year>
            <month>08</month>
            <day>29</day>
            <uri>https://publications.dainst.org/journals/zaak/article/view/4178</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.34780/AKD6-046J</pub-id>
            <fpage>251284 Seiten</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-schmidt2014-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rapp Py-Daniel</surname>
                <given-names>Anne</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Paula Moraes</surname>
                <given-names>Claide</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Valle</surname>
                <given-names>Raoni B. M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Caromano</surname>
                <given-names>Caroline F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Texeira</surname>
                <given-names>Wenceslau G.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barbosa</surname>
                <given-names>Carlos A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fonseca</surname>
                <given-names>João A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Magalhães</surname>
                <given-names>Marcos P.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Silva Do Carmo Santos</surname>
                <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Da Silva E Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Renan</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Guapindaia</surname>
                <given-names>Vera L.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Moraes</surname>
                <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lima</surname>
                <given-names>Helena P.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Neves</surname>
                <given-names>Eduardo G.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
                <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Dark earths and the human built landscape in Amazonia: a widespread pattern of anthrosol formation</article-title>
            <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2014-02">2014</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <volume>42</volume>
            <uri>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0305440313003889</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jas.2013.11.002</pub-id>
            <fpage>152</fpage>
            <lpage>165</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-palace2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Palace</surname>
                <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>McMichael</surname>
                <given-names>C. N. H.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Braswell</surname>
                <given-names>B. H.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hagen</surname>
                <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Bush</surname>
                <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Neves</surname>
                <given-names>E.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Tamanaha</surname>
                <given-names>E.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Herrick</surname>
                <given-names>C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Frolking</surname>
                <given-names>S.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Ancient Amazonian populations left lasting impacts on forest structure</article-title>
            <source>Ecosphere</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017-12">2017</year>
            <month>12</month>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <issue>12</issue>
            <uri>https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ecs2.2035</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ecs2.2035</pub-id>
            <fpage>e02035</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-goldberg2024-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Goldberg</surname>
                <given-names>Samuel L.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Himmelstein</surname>
                <given-names>Joshua D.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
                <given-names>Michael</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Franchetto</surname>
                <given-names>Bruna</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lima</surname>
                <given-names>Helena</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Watling</surname>
                <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Moraes</surname>
                <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Dorshow</surname>
                <given-names>Wetherbee B.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fausto</surname>
                <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Waura</surname>
                <given-names>Kumessi</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
                <given-names>Huke</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
                <given-names>Taku Wate</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
                <given-names>Afukaka</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Perron</surname>
                <given-names>J. Taylor</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Widespread Amazonian dark earth in the Xingu Indigenous Territory</article-title>
            <source>Nature Sustainability</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2024-07-26">2024</year>
            <month>07</month>
            <day>26</day>
            <volume>7</volume>
            <issue>10</issue>
            <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-024-01399-3</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-024-01399-3</pub-id>
            <fpage>1304</fpage>
            <lpage>1312</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-peripato2023-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Peripato</surname>
                <given-names>Vinicius</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Levis</surname>
                <given-names>Carolina</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Moreira</surname>
                <given-names>Guido A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gamerman</surname>
                <given-names>Dani</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ter Steege</surname>
                <given-names>Hans</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pitman</surname>
                <given-names>Nigel C. A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Souza</surname>
                <given-names>Jonas G.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Iriarte</surname>
                <given-names>José</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Robinson</surname>
                <given-names>Mark</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Junqueira</surname>
                <given-names>André Braga</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Trindade</surname>
                <given-names>Thiago B.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Almeida</surname>
                <given-names>Fernando O.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Moraes</surname>
                <given-names>Claide De Paula</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lombardo</surname>
                <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Tamanaha</surname>
                <given-names>Eduardo K.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Maezumi</surname>
                <given-names>Shira Y.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ometto</surname>
                <given-names>Jean P. H. B.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Braga</surname>
                <given-names>José R. G.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Campanharo</surname>
                <given-names>Wesley A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cassol</surname>
                <given-names>Henrique L. G.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Leal</surname>
                <given-names>Philipe R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Assis</surname>
                <given-names>Mauro L. R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Da Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Adriana M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Phillips</surname>
                <given-names>Oliver L.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Costa</surname>
                <given-names>Flávia R. C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Flores</surname>
                <given-names>Bernardo Monteiro</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Henkel</surname>
                <given-names>Terry W.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Umaña</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Natalia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Magnusson</surname>
                <given-names>William E.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Valderrama Sandoval</surname>
                <given-names>Elvis H.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barlow</surname>
                <given-names>Jos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Milliken</surname>
                <given-names>William</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lopes</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Aparecida</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Simon</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelo Fragomeni</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Van Andel</surname>
                <given-names>Tinde R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Laurance</surname>
                <given-names>Susan G. W.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Laurance</surname>
                <given-names>William F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Torres-Lezama</surname>
                <given-names>Armando</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Assis</surname>
                <given-names>Rafael L.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Molino</surname>
                <given-names>Jean-François</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mestre</surname>
                <given-names>Mickaël</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hamblin</surname>
                <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Coelho</surname>
                <given-names>Luiz De Souza</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lima Filho</surname>
                <given-names>Diogenes De Andrade</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Wittmann</surname>
                <given-names>Florian</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Salomão</surname>
                <given-names>Rafael P.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Amaral</surname>
                <given-names>Iêda Leão</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Guevara</surname>
                <given-names>Juan Ernesto</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Almeida Matos</surname>
                <given-names>Francisca Dionízia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Castilho</surname>
                <given-names>Carolina V.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Carim</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelo De Jesus Veiga</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cárdenas López</surname>
                <given-names>Dairon</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Sabatier</surname>
                <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Irume</surname>
                <given-names>Mariana Victória</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Martins</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Pires</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Guimarães</surname>
                <given-names>José Renan Da Silva</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Bánki</surname>
                <given-names>Olaf S.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Piedade</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Teresa Fernandez</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ramos</surname>
                <given-names>José Ferreira</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Luize</surname>
                <given-names>Bruno Garcia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Novo</surname>
                <given-names>Evlyn Márcia Moraes De Leão</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Núñez Vargas</surname>
                <given-names>Percy</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Thiago Sanna Freire</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Venticinque</surname>
                <given-names>Eduardo Martins</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Manzatto</surname>
                <given-names>Angelo Gilberto</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Reis</surname>
                <given-names>Neidiane Farias Costa</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Terborgh</surname>
                <given-names>John</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Casula</surname>
                <given-names>Katia Regina</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Demarchi</surname>
                <given-names>Layon O.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Honorio Coronado</surname>
                <given-names>Euridice N.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Monteagudo Mendoza</surname>
                <given-names>Abel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Montero</surname>
                <given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schöngart</surname>
                <given-names>Jochen</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Feldpausch</surname>
                <given-names>Ted R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Quaresma</surname>
                <given-names>Adriano Costa</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Aymard C.</surname>
                <given-names>Gerardo A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Baraloto</surname>
                <given-names>Chris</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Castaño Arboleda</surname>
                <given-names>Nicolás</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Engel</surname>
                <given-names>Julien</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Petronelli</surname>
                <given-names>Pascal</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Zartman</surname>
                <given-names>Charles Eugene</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Killeen</surname>
                <given-names>Timothy J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Marimon</surname>
                <given-names>Beatriz S.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Marimon-Junior</surname>
                <given-names>Ben Hur</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schietti</surname>
                <given-names>Juliana</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Sousa</surname>
                <given-names>Thaiane R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vasquez</surname>
                <given-names>Rodolfo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rincón</surname>
                <given-names>Lorena M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Berenguer</surname>
                <given-names>Erika</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                <given-names>Joice</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mostacedo</surname>
                <given-names>Bonifacio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Do Amaral</surname>
                <given-names>Dário Dantas</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Castellanos</surname>
                <given-names>Hernán</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Medeiros</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelo Brilhante</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Andrade</surname>
                <given-names>Ana</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Camargo</surname>
                <given-names>José Luís</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Farias</surname>
                <given-names>Emanuelle De Sousa</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Magalhães</surname>
                <given-names>José Leonardo Lima</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mendonça Nascimento</surname>
                <given-names>Henrique Eduardo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Queiroz</surname>
                <given-names>Helder Lima</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Brienen</surname>
                <given-names>Roel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cardenas Revilla</surname>
                <given-names>Juan David</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Stevenson</surname>
                <given-names>Pablo R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Araujo-Murakami</surname>
                <given-names>Alejandro</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barçante Ladvocat Cintra</surname>
                <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Feitosa</surname>
                <given-names>Yuri Oliveira</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barbosa</surname>
                <given-names>Flávia Rodrigues</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Carpanedo</surname>
                <given-names>Rainiellen De Sá</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Duivenvoorden</surname>
                <given-names>Joost F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Noronha</surname>
                <given-names>Janaína Da Costa</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                <given-names>Domingos De Jesus</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mogollón</surname>
                <given-names>Hugo F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                <given-names>Leandro Valle</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Householder</surname>
                <given-names>John Ethan</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lozada</surname>
                <given-names>José Rafael</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Comiskey</surname>
                <given-names>James A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Draper</surname>
                <given-names>Freddie C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Toledo</surname>
                <given-names>José Julio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Damasco</surname>
                <given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Dávila</surname>
                <given-names>Nállarett</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>García-Villacorta</surname>
                <given-names>Roosevelt</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lopes</surname>
                <given-names>Aline</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cornejo Valverde</surname>
                <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Alonso</surname>
                <given-names>Alfonso</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Dallmeier</surname>
                <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gomes</surname>
                <given-names>Vitor H. F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Jimenez</surname>
                <given-names>Eliana M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Neill</surname>
                <given-names>David</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Peñuela Mora</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Cristina</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Aguiar</surname>
                <given-names>Daniel P. P.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Arroyo</surname>
                <given-names>Luzmila</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Antunes Carvalho</surname>
                <given-names>Fernanda</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Coelho De Souza</surname>
                <given-names>Fernanda</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Feeley</surname>
                <given-names>Kenneth J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gribel</surname>
                <given-names>Rogerio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pansonato</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelo Petratti</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ríos Paredes</surname>
                <given-names>Marcos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Brasil Da Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Izaias</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                <given-names>Maria Julia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fine</surname>
                <given-names>Paul V. A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fonty</surname>
                <given-names>Émile</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Guedes</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelino Carneiro</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Licona</surname>
                <given-names>Juan Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pennington</surname>
                <given-names>Toby</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Peres</surname>
                <given-names>Carlos A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Villa Zegarra</surname>
                <given-names>Boris Eduardo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Parada</surname>
                <given-names>Germaine Alexander</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pardo Molina</surname>
                <given-names>Guido</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vos</surname>
                <given-names>Vincent Antoine</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cerón</surname>
                <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Maas</surname>
                <given-names>Paul</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Silveira</surname>
                <given-names>Marcos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Stropp</surname>
                <given-names>Juliana</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Thomas</surname>
                <given-names>Raquel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Baker</surname>
                <given-names>Tim R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Daly</surname>
                <given-names>Doug</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Huamantupa-Chuquimaco</surname>
                <given-names>Isau</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vieira</surname>
                <given-names>Ima Célia Guimarães</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Weiss Albuquerque</surname>
                <given-names>Bianca</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fuentes</surname>
                <given-names>Alfredo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Klitgaard</surname>
                <given-names>Bente</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Marcelo-Peña</surname>
                <given-names>José Luis</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Silman</surname>
                <given-names>Miles R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Tello</surname>
                <given-names>J. Sebastián</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vriesendorp</surname>
                <given-names>Corine</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Chave</surname>
                <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Di Fiore</surname>
                <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hilário</surname>
                <given-names>Renato Richard</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Phillips</surname>
                <given-names>Juan Fernando</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rivas-Torres</surname>
                <given-names>Gonzalo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Von Hildebrand</surname>
                <given-names>Patricio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pereira</surname>
                <given-names>Luciana De Oliveira</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barbosa</surname>
                <given-names>Edelcilio Marques</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Matos Bonates</surname>
                <given-names>Luiz Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Doza</surname>
                <given-names>Hilda Paulette Dávila</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Zárate Gómez</surname>
                <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gallardo Gonzales</surname>
                <given-names>George Pepe</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gonzales</surname>
                <given-names>Therany</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Malhi</surname>
                <given-names>Yadvinder</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Andrade Miranda</surname>
                <given-names>Ires Paula</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mozombite Pinto</surname>
                <given-names>Linder Felipe</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Prieto</surname>
                <given-names>Adriana</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rudas</surname>
                <given-names>Agustín</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ruschel</surname>
                <given-names>Ademir R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Natalino</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vela</surname>
                <given-names>César I. A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Zent</surname>
                <given-names>Egleé L.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Zent</surname>
                <given-names>Stanford</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cano</surname>
                <given-names>Angela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Carrero Márquez</surname>
                <given-names>Yrma Andreina</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Correa</surname>
                <given-names>Diego F.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Costa</surname>
                <given-names>Janaina Barbosa Pedrosa</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Galbraith</surname>
                <given-names>David</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Holmgren</surname>
                <given-names>Milena</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kalamandeen</surname>
                <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Lobo</surname>
                <given-names>Guilherme</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Nascimento</surname>
                <given-names>Marcelo Trindade</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                <given-names>Alexandre A.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ramirez-Angulo</surname>
                <given-names>Hirma</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Rocha</surname>
                <given-names>Maira</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Scudeller</surname>
                <given-names>Veridiana Vizoni</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Sierra</surname>
                <given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Tirado</surname>
                <given-names>Milton</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Van Der Heijden</surname>
                <given-names>Geertje</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vilanova Torre</surname>
                <given-names>Emilio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ahuite Reategui</surname>
                <given-names>Manuel Augusto</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Baider</surname>
                <given-names>Cláudia</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Balslev</surname>
                <given-names>Henrik</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cárdenas</surname>
                <given-names>Sasha</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Casas</surname>
                <given-names>Luisa Fernanda</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Farfan-Rios</surname>
                <given-names>William</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                <given-names>Cid</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Linares-Palomino</surname>
                <given-names>Reynaldo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mendoza</surname>
                <given-names>Casimiro</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Mesones</surname>
                <given-names>Italo</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Urrego Giraldo</surname>
                <given-names>Ligia Estela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Villarroel</surname>
                <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Zagt</surname>
                <given-names>Roderick</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Alexiades</surname>
                <given-names>Miguel N.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>De Oliveira</surname>
                <given-names>Edmar Almeida</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Garcia-Cabrera</surname>
                <given-names>Karina</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hernandez</surname>
                <given-names>Lionel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Palacios Cuenca</surname>
                <given-names>Walter</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pansini</surname>
                <given-names>Susamar</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pauletto</surname>
                <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ramirez Arevalo</surname>
                <given-names>Fredy</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Sampaio</surname>
                <given-names>Adeilza Felipe</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Valenzuela Gamarra</surname>
                <given-names>Luis</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Aragão</surname>
                <given-names>Luiz E. O. C.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>More than 10,000 pre-Columbian earthworks are still hidden throughout Amazonia</article-title>
            <source>Science</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-10-06">2023</year>
            <month>10</month>
            <day>06</day>
            <volume>382</volume>
            <issue>6666</issue>
            <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ade2541</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.ade2541</pub-id>
            <fpage>103</fpage>
            <lpage>109</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-desouza2018-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>De Souza</surname>
                <given-names>Jonas Gregorio</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schaan</surname>
                <given-names>Denise Pahl</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Robinson</surname>
                <given-names>Mark</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Barbosa</surname>
                <given-names>Antonia Damasceno</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Aragão</surname>
                <given-names>Luiz E. O. C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Marimon</surname>
                <given-names>Ben Hur</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Marimon</surname>
                <given-names>Beatriz Schwantes</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Da Silva</surname>
                <given-names>Izaias Brasil</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Khan</surname>
                <given-names>Salman Saeed</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Nakahara</surname>
                <given-names>Francisco Ruji</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Iriarte</surname>
                <given-names>José</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Pre-Columbian earth-builders settled along the entire southern rim of the Amazon</article-title>
            <source>Nature Communications</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2018-03-27">2018</year>
            <month>03</month>
            <day>27</day>
            <volume>9</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-03510-7</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03510-7</pub-id>
            <fpage>1125</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-erickson2000-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Erickson</surname>
                <given-names>Clark L</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>An artificial landscape-scale fishery in the Bolivian Amazon</article-title>
            <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
            <volume>408</volume>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-heckenberger2008-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Heckenberger</surname>
                <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Russell</surname>
                <given-names>J. Christian</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Fausto</surname>
                <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Toney</surname>
                <given-names>Joshua R.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                <given-names>Morgan J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pereira</surname>
                <given-names>Edithe</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Franchetto</surname>
                <given-names>Bruna</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kuikuro</surname>
                <given-names>Afukaka</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Pre-Columbian Urbanism, Anthropogenic Landscapes, and the Future of the Amazon</article-title>
            <source>Science</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2008-08-29">2008</year>
            <month>08</month>
            <day>29</day>
            <volume>321</volume>
            <issue>5893</issue>
            <uri>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.1159769</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1159769</pub-id>
            <fpage>1214</fpage>
            <lpage>1217</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </sub-article>
  <sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-2-nb-1">
    <front-stub>
</front-stub>
    <body>
      <p>GPT counter prompt</p>
      <sec id="role-nb-1">
        <title>Role</title>
        <p>Remote-sensing analyst detecting/counting pre-Columbian Amazonian
  anthrosol (terra preta/ADE) forest patches. These nutrient-rich soils
  (800–2500 BP) from ancient farming, burning, waste deposition create
  distinct vegetation: drier, lower-stature forest with palms, fruit
  trees, lianas—agroforestry remnants. Patches typically enclosed by
  earthwork ditches (deep, meters wide), may connect via linear
  earthworks (canals, roads) appearing as faint CHM lines or subtle
  taller-tree lines in C2. Ancient managed landscapes: patches form part
  of broader agroforestry-settlement systems; spatial patterning,
  drainage alignment, and earthwork traces key for interpretation
  alongside spectral-structural signals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="inputs-nb-1">
        <title>Inputs</title>
        <p><bold>C1 (false-color RGB)</bold>: R=B12 SWIR₂, G=B4 red, B=B2 blue
  Vegetation moisture/stress at ~10m.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Stressed/dry: bright red/pink/magenta</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Healthier/wetter veg or soil: darker red/purple, wet/swampy
      vegetation light purple/green/black</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Water: blue or black</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Forest matrix: mottled, bumpy texture</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Nonforest/floodplain/outcrop: bare soil smooth bright white or
      light blue or pale pink</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Earthworks faintly visible as subtle lines of taller
      purple/black trees</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>C2 (false-color RGB)</bold>: R=B9 water vapor absorption,
  G=B11 SWIR₁, B=B2 blue
  Canopy evapotranspiration at ~10m (B9 downsampled from 60m →
  diffuse).</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Low transpiration (dry): bright yellow/orange (target patches:
      bright yellow splotches, red-orange/lime green near center)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Forest canopy: mottled red/orange</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Moist canopy/wet soil: dark blue/purple/black</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Water/wet soil: blue or black</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Sedgy vegetation: dull red/purple/blue mix</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>CHM (canopy height map)</bold>: 0–35m: black=0m →
  purple/blue=low → green=mid → yellow=high
  Identifies clearings, canopy gaps.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="target-pattern-nb-1">
        <title>Target Pattern</title>
        <p><bold>Context</bold>: Compact anomaly in continuous forest matrix
  (mottled C1 texture) or at forest edge above floodplain; aligned along
  bluff edges, fractal drainages, or settlement networks; often
  patterned, spaced, or linked by faint linear earthwork traces
  (ditches, canals, roads).</p>
        <p><bold>Form</bold>: Compact, lobate, elliptical, clustered; not
  diffuse.</p>
        <p><bold>Size</bold>: ≥5 ha (≥20 px); typical 5–700 ha.</p>
        <p><bold>Spectral-structural combo</bold>:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>C1: bright red/pink/magenta patch or ring; taller darker
      purple/black trees may appear in center or radiate between patches
      (earthworks)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>C2: supporting yellow/orange zone (may be broader/diffuse)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>CHM: optional low canopy patch, ring; may look less regular
      than spectral signature; lower canopy within or at edges</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="exclusions-nb-1">
        <title>Exclusions</title>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Forest-nonforest boundaries (forest islands) ≠ forest-in-forest
      ADE patches</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Isolated small blobs/spikes (&lt;20 px or lacking form)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>CHM-only anomalies without spectral support</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Recent disturbances (e.g. logging, swidden agriculture)
      yielding sharper land-use mosaics</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Broad diffuse stressed zones lacking compact core, unusual
      shape, or context fit</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Anomalies visible in only one spectral image without supporting
      context</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>land-use boundaries, forest-nonforest edges, matrix composition
      differences — not compact anomalies within forest matrix</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="workflow-nb-1">
        <title>Workflow</title>
        <p>
          <bold>Scene interpretation</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Integrate C1, C2, CHM holistically. Identify compact, plausible
  ADE-like anomalies with supporting form, spectral pattern, location.
  <bold>Directly estimate count of valid patches.</bold> If no valid
  candidates exist, return <monospace>0</monospace>. If valid candidates
  exist, return the count (max 30).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="reasoning-style-nb-1">
        <title>Reasoning Style</title>
        <p>Dense, concise, nontrivial reasoning chains. Prioritize facts,
  spatial context, spectral-structural meaning. Avoid filler. Holistic:
  integrate spectral, spatial, form, terrain, ecology, archaeology.
  Spatial fit and form over raw spectral strength. P<bold>erform full
  expert reasoning silently. Return only the final count (max 30). No
  other text.</bold></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="examples-nb-1">
        <title>Examples</title>
        <p><bold>Example 1 — No valid patches</bold>
  Observation: Lobate forest islands on floodplain; no compact canopy
  anomaly within continuous forest. C2 no yellow. CHM no features.
  0</p>
        <p><bold>Example 2 — Single compact patch</bold>
  Observation: Compact magenta patch C1 (30 px) at terrace edge above
  floodplain. C2 yellow. CHM partial low ring.
  1</p>
        <p><bold>Example 3 — Cluster of patches</bold>
  Observation: Two compact red-pink anomalies (25 px) along bluff. C2
  yellow. CHM low canopy between, faint tree line connects.
  2</p>
        <p><bold>Example 4 — Complex scene</bold>
  Observation: Multiple irregular reddish anomalies along fractal
  drainage on bluff edge. C2 diffuse yellow. CHM partial height breaks.
  5</p>
        <p><bold>Example 5 — Broad stressed zone</bold>
  Observation: Large reddish zone C1 (~100 px) on terrace above
  floodplain; C2 diffuse yellow; no clear CHM anomaly. Natural variation
  or land-use gradient.
  1</p>
      </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
</back>
  </sub-article>
  <sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-4-nb-2">
    <front-stub>
</front-stub>
    <body>
      <sec id="gptmoondream-object-detection-prompt-nb-2">
        <title>GPT/Moondream Object Detection Prompt</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="role-nb-2">
        <title>Role</title>
        <p>Remote-sensing analyst detecting/counting pre-Columbian Amazonian
  anthrosol (terra preta/ADE) forest patches. These nutrient-rich soils
  (800–2500 BP) from ancient farming, burning, waste deposition create
  distinct vegetation: drier, lower-stature forest with palms, fruit
  trees, lianas—agroforestry remnants. Patches typically enclosed by
  earthwork ditches (deep, meters wide), may connect via linear
  earthworks (canals, roads) appearing as faint CHM lines or subtle
  taller-tree lines in C2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="inputs-nb-2">
        <title>Inputs</title>
        <p><bold>C1 (false-color RGB)</bold>: R=B12 SWIR₂, G=B4 red, B=B2 blue
  Vegetation moisture/stress at ~10m. - Stressed/dry: bright
  red/pink/magenta - Healthier/wetter veg or soil: darker red/purple,
  wet/swampy vegetation is light purple/green/black - Water is blue or
  black - Forest matrix: mottled, bumpy texture -
  Nonforest/floodplain/outcrop: bare soil smooth bright white or light
  blue or pale pink - Earthworks faintly visible as subtle lines of
  taller trees purple/black trees</p>
        <p><bold>C2 (false-color RGB)</bold>: R=B9 water vapor absorption,
  G=B11 SWIR₁, B=B2 blue
  Canopy evapotranspiration at ~10m (B9 downsampled from 60m → diffuse).
  - Low transpiration (dry): bright yellow/orange (target patches look
  like bright yellow splotches, some with red-orange or lime green
  touches near center) - Forest canopy mottled red/orange - Moist
  canopy/wet soil: dark blue/purple/black - Water and wet soil is blue
  or black - Sedgy vegetation dull red/purple/blue mix</p>
        <p><bold>CHM (canopy height map)</bold>: 0–35m: black=0m →
  purple/blue=low → green=mid → yellow=high
  Identifies clearings, canopy gaps.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="target-pattern-nb-2">
        <title>Target Pattern</title>
        <p><bold>Context</bold>: Compact anomaly in continuous forest matrix
  (mottled C1 texture) or at forest edge above floodplain; aligned along
  bluff edges, fractal drainages, or settlement networks; often
  patterned, spaced, or linked by faint linear earthwork traces
  (ditches, canals, roads). These are traces of ancient human
  agroforestry-settlement systems; so spatial patterning, drainage
  alignment, and earthwork traces aid interpretation alongside
  spectral-structural signals.</p>
        <p><bold>Form</bold>: Compact, lobate, elliptical, clustered; not
  diffuse.</p>
        <p><bold>Size</bold>: ≥5 ha (≥20 px); typical 5–700 ha.</p>
        <p><bold>Spectral-structural combo</bold>: - C1: bright
  red/pink/magenta patch or ring, taller darker purple/black trees may
  be present in center or radiating between patches in faint linear
  connection (earthworks) - C2: supporting yellow/orange zone (may be
  broader/diffuse) - CHM: optional low canopy patch, ring. May look less
  regular than spectral signature. Height anomalies (lower vegetation)
  appear WITHIN patches OR as rings/edges AROUND patches</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="exclusions-nb-2">
        <title>Exclusions</title>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Forest-nonforest boundaries (forest islands) ≠ forest-in-forest
      ADE patches</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Isolated small blobs/spikes (&lt;20 px or lacking form)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>CHM-only anomalies without spectral support</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Recent disturbances (e.g. logging, swidden agriculture)
      yielding sharper land-use mosaics</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Broad diffuse stressed zones lacking compact core, unusual
      shape, or context fit</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Anomalies visible in only one spectral image without supporting
      context</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Detections where colored patches are simply discrete forest
      islands within non-forest matrix (e.g. swamps, floodplain,
      clearings); true anomalies are distinct vegetation differences
      within continuous forest canopy.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="workflow-nb-2">
        <title>Workflow</title>
        <p><bold>1️⃣ Scene interpretation</bold>
  Integrate C1, C2, CHM holistically. Identify compact, plausible
  ADE-like anomalies with supporting form, spectral pattern, location.
  If no valid candidates exist, complete analysis immediately and say
  DONE, do not use Moondream. If valid candidates exist, provide initial
  count estimate based on expert interpretation before tool use.</p>
        <p><bold>2️⃣ Moondream object detection loop (C1 only)</bold>
  Use ONLY if valid anomalies identified. Lets you determine exact point
  locations of anomalies from text prompts. Simple abstract prompts
  (color + shape): “reddish-pink spots”, “large magenta patch”, “lobate
  red blobs”. Plural terms better unless targeting specific object.
  Start with one basic descriptor; if misses obvious patches then
  iterate/branch with different prompts. Parallel tool calls allowed. At
  least two tool calls unless very confident in firest result. Max 10
  iterations. Returns normalized coordinates (0–1). You control tool
  use; Moondream provides locations—you synthesize final result.</p>
        <p><bold>3️⃣ Synthesis</bold>
  Combine points from multiple tool calls. Don’t make up points. Max 30
  points per image. Remove redundant points; each represents distinct
  compact patch. Validate: dual spectral support, compact form, context
  fit, ≥5 ha. Patches near image edge acceptable if consistent with
  broader context of scene. BRIEFLY describe synthesis of points.</p>
        <p><bold>4️⃣ Finish</bold>
  When synthesis complete, say DONE. User will prompt for final results,
  only then provide JSON with final synthesis points:</p>
        <p>``` json { “count”: , “points”: [{“items”: [x, y]}],
  “detection_summary”: { “prompts”: [“…”], “notes”: “≤5 concise bullets
  summarizing reasoning” } }</p>
      </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
</back>
  </sub-article>
</article>
